[Music]
Hey, hey,
hey. Heat. Heat.
[Music]
Hello. So, good evening, good day
everybody and welcome to to the 250th
episode of the Ask Abijit Show.
Incredible that we are here episode 250.
It's a long way. So, it's all thanks to
you that I've reached episode 250.
Thanks to your viewership, thanks to
your participation. So, thank you all so
very much for being on this journey. Uh,
so let's see who are there in the live
chat. I'll greet you all. I can see Mr.
Reactor Zone, Aluminati Creek, Shashank
Koshik, Event Countdown, Rajat Duhan,
the world teacher,
uh, Geopolitical Dub, Raju Jangra, Kumar
Koshik, Kumar Kanesh, Mano Si, Pratik,
Goyel, Sonu, Bharav, Anandpai, Mr. 88,
Anime Bal, Aayushman, Matur, Praal,
Gupa, Sharma, Pamel Gandhi, Arpita,
Shukla, Narendra, Reddi, he
tancha, Mr. 8 years again anonymous
scientist info king Samriti Gowwami
Rahul Lakshmaran unknown Hitanchu again
Abhinav Maklavin he hey he Aush yadav
uh Captain Price 451
knock Mishra
Araana Shubhham Jan Pulkit Gupta Aditya
Singh Aris Manticor World leaders Arun
Sahi Matt's person Tushar X chitan Ara
Radia Palin, Tanay Chandra, Jeet Mitra,
Aditya, Kuml, Janovi, Priyanka, Javalia,
Ashish, Pandel, Rishab, Dang, Prabhav,
Krypa, Prahar S. uh who else do we have?
I can see Tanud Sharma, Duv Durya,
Biplabda, Shashang Singh, Shivan, Shiv,
Shiva, Daran, S, Shashank, Mr.
Tanzanj Shashi Kiran Mayor Malini
uh Shri Kantu Tupurani Shivatsa Kajoro
Bthorn Mohit but with Amarjit Thirumal
RC Mr. Jam Rajendulkar and so many other
people. Thank you so much all of you for
being on the live chat. So once again
I'm going to take questions from the
super chat. I will also as far as
possible take questions from the regular
chat as well. But I tried this
experiment with the super chat last week
and I saw that it's a whole different
quality of questions. All questions are
serious. There is no fluff. So I have
decided to continue with the super chat
experiment and I'll answer as many of
these super chat questions and other
questions also if possible as many as I
can. So uh before I get into that uh
it's almost four years since I started
this uh journey of askit. I started the
first episode of askabit went live on
the 2nd of June
2021. So it's going to be day after
tomorrow is going to be the fourth
anniversary of askit. So on the 2nd of
June 2025 I'm starting something new.
I'm starting Geio Strategy with Abijit
Chava and the first episode will go live
on the 2nd of June. That's day after
tomorrow at 8:00 p.m. It's going to be a
four times a week thing all live. It
will be followed by Askabit. So you're
going to you can expect a lot more
content and very very focused content on
this channel going forward. That's
coming up next week Monday. I'll put a
whole schedule for the next week
tomorrow. So I look forward to having
you in that as well. Okay, let's get
going with the questions. I can see this
question by Mr. Aers. Why didn't M help
PK? What's
UM? Help PK Pakistan become an economic
giant like Japan, Deutschand, Korea. Uh
you mean US, I suppose. Um so they
became giants, economic giants to
countering USSR invasion in Afghanistan.
Who's going to win UCL tonight? Okay.
Okay. um why didn't the US I suppose
help Pakistan become an economic giant
because see every country has a separate
kind of utility when you are the haman
the global hedge the superpower you see
different portions different parts
different regions of the world through
different lenses and each region has a
set of actors geopolitical actors and
you assign a certain utility utility to
each actor so certain cultures may not
be conducive to certain kinds of actions
and so on and so forth. So the Americans
physically and militarily occupied Japan
and Korea and you know transform those
nations into economic powers and uh and
manufacturing powers and technological
powers and they leveraged that they used
that to to to further their hold on the
world. Pakistan was seen through a
different lens. For a long time it was a
nation which could you know
counterbalance India. Then with the
Afghanistan invasion on Christmas day 20
in 1979 it acquired a whole different
dimension. So it it's because they saw
the the the nation of Pakistan through a
different lens and they assigned a
different kind of utility to the nation.
So that's why Pakistan never became an
economic giant became a terrorist giant.
The world's greatest exporter of
terrorism. The world's epicenter of
terrorism. Who's going to win? UCLet.
I'm not really sure. I'm not really
following it. I have don't have the time
to follow a lot of sports these days.
Unfortunately, I would love to, but
don't get the
time. Utkar says, "All AI models are
scary. Good. India's low medium skill
service jobs will be gone in 3 years.
Even the West will be hit hard as 95% of
service jobs will be replaced. How do we
prepare for the future? It's going to be
difficult." And you know, the future is
coming. I I think uh I don't know who it
was. The head of uh one of the biggest
one of one of the large AI companies I
think it was I think it was Fiverr. The
head of Fiverr I think said that you
know everybody needs to prepare for mass
layoffs and all that because AI is going
to take over most jobs. AI is getting
good with agentic capabilities. AI can
do stuff that you know you typically
would have an intern or an entry- level
employee do. all that repetitive
automated tasks AI can take over now. It
can do it. You can, you know, have
multiple AI employees, agents doing work
for you that typically you would have
human employees do. We are already at
that stage. So AI is going to take away
a lot of jobs, right?
certain sectors are going to be uh you
know it'll be hard for AI to to intrude
in those sectors but overall it's it's
uh it's dangerous times for uh you know
people who are who have been stuck in a
certain niche or certain industry for a
very long time and who who are very safe
and who feel very safe and secure entire
industries are going to be completely
transformed for example the IT industry
is going to be completely transformed by
AI it's going to be a very bad time for
the Indian IT industry. For example,
because so much of code can be taken
care of by AI today. You can start a
startup as a one-man founder with
nothing but AI tools, AI employees. If
you understand it, if you understand
code, if you understand application
design, if you know how to you know
create formulate detailed requirements,
detailed designs based on the those
requirements, then you can if you have
an understanding of the process, then
you can have everything done by AI. If
you have no idea and you think you can
vibe code through the things, you will
get nowhere. But you have a good
background, solid understanding, then a
one person team can start a startup
today with AI. So you know all these
lots of these low and medium skill jobs
like Utkash is saying are going to be
wiped out by AI. It makes no sense to
hire human employees. Okay. No economic
sense. It makes no economic or strategic
sense to hire 10 human employees. Spend
a lot of time training them and then
someday they'll fall sick. Someday they
will have a day off. Sometimes their
mood will not be great. Some some of
them don't work very well. There's a lot
of turnover. It's not hard. It's not
easy to find good employees. Very hard
to find good employees. So there's going
to be a turnover rate. Instead of that,
you just hire you just, you know, get a
bunch of AI agents, 10 AI agents and and
you also have to train those AI agents.
No, no question about it. But once the
training is done, it's
done, right? So a lot of these low and
medium skill jobs are going to be
replaced especially in the fields of IT
in and lots of other fields as well.
uh today you don't need to uh for
example if you are in in video
production a lot of video editing can be
done through AI automation a lot of it
not all of it but a lot of it uh so you
know it's only at the high high end that
human intervention is needed all the
basic stuff can be done by AI that's
where we are and in 2 three years even
that high-end stuff will be done by AI
most likely and it's not just India as
the west that's going to be hit hard
everyone's going to be hit hard a lot of
these service jobs which which require
have low level human interaction will be
uh will become redundant. AI can now
make calls on behalf of you and act like
a human person and it it sounds
convincing right? So AI can do a lot.
What can what do we do to prepare for
this future is the question utkar is
asking. You have to be so what what
should the the average person do who is
in so and so industry? You have to very
quickly adapt to this. You have to learn
how to acquire new skills very
rapidly. That's the only only solution.
You have to become AI native. You have
to see the jobs that will exist in the
future are though are that of manager
managerial positions, managing teams of
AI workers, that sort of thing. Um yeah,
so you're going to have to learn how to
adapt. You're going to have to learn how
to acquire new skills rapidly. The most
important skill today is to learn how to
learn fast. Learn new things fast. And
people who refuse to learn are going to
be left behind. I know a lot of people
especially older folks folks who are
not, you know, they're they're terrible
with technology. They don't know how to
use mobile phones, laptops, whatever.
Those people, I'm sorry, if you don't ad
adapt, then you're going to be left
behind. So everybody is going to have to
become conversant with with technology
and the be the most important skill is
how to learn quickly, how to adapt
quickly, how to acquire new schools
skills very rapidly. That's what's
needed. Manikandan says, "What do you
think of the recent statement by our CDS
visav the narrative game? What's the
realignment against Batin's operation
Synindor?" So today I saw on social
media the news came out that our chief
of defense staff gave an interview to I
think Bloomberg and looks like he has
made a statement that kind of indicates
that we may have lost uh fighter plane
or two or something. No numbers were
given but the statement sounds like he's
a kind of you could conrue it to mean
that he admitted that we lost u at least
one aircraft.
My question is why does the chief of
defense staff have to give an interview
to
Bloomberg? I just don't understand what
we are trying to achieve by doing this.
I don't care if we lost one F-16, one
whatever aircraft or five or whatever.
It doesn't matter. Recently the
Americans were were doing this military
operations against the Houthis. They
lost two
F-18s. Did the world make a human cry
about that? No. But the world is trying
to make a human cry about India about us
proper perpetually uh allegedly losing I
don't know whatever number of aircraft
during that uh 3-day war against
Pakistan operation zindur we achieved
all our objectives we smashed Pakistan
but the world tries the media etc
they're trying to you know say that if
India lost x number of fighter planes
maybe one maybe two whatever then it's a
loss for India my question is why does
India's chief of defense staff have to
go and give an give an interview to
Bloomberg to an American media outlet.
For what reason is this
required? These folks the American media
they are blatantly anti-India. Why do we
have to go to them and give them the
privilege of interviewing our chief of
defense staff? I just don't understand
it. It is incomprehensible to me. So
what do I think of this recent
statement? I think it is
incomprehensible. I think it is a self
goal. I don't know what our CDS is
doing. Is it doing this on his own or
was he ordered? Was he instructed to go
and speak to Bloomberg? If he was
instructed to go and speak to Bloomberg
Bloomberg, then who gave him the
instructions and for what reason? How
does it serve our national interest?
Every single
thing a government or military official
is does, every single thing is supposed
to serve the national interest. In what
way does the CDS giving an interview to
Bloomberg and saying whatever he said,
how does it serve the national interest?
It doesn't serve the national interest
according to me. Maybe I'm completely,
you know, clueless,
huh? But I failed to see how it serves
our national interest. So what was the
the objective of what the CDS did? I
just don't get it. I failed to
understand. I failed to comprehend.
Maybe my IQ is too
low but I just this is incomprehensible
to me right so that's all I have to say
about this what's the realignment
against bat against operation the same
old same old stuff the western media is
against us the and they are trying to
push the Pakistani narrative uh lots of
I mean there's more and more evidences
emerging about the strikes India did
about the details of the strikes and the
damage it caused on Pakistani military
installations air force bases and so on
and zero evidence is coming
of any hit the Pakistanis may have done
or may have claimed to do on other
infrastructure. Zero, not a shred of
evidence and not a shred of evidence of
an Indian aircraft going down.
But but the media is arrayed against us
and that's what we should expect. That's
how it goes. But I don't understand why
our chief of defense staff has to go to
the enemy and give an interview to the
white man or the white man's
organization.
What is it? Is it an inferiority complex
thing? What what exactly is it? I just
don't get it. It is incomprehensible.
Most likely I'm just not intelligent
enough to understand what the game
is. Kumar Kaneshka says, "Why are we so
lacking in information warfare globally,
especially from Western India? It's not
like we need any validation from the
west, but it looks bad as our image is
so tarnished and perception matters
today. We can fight our own information
warfare if we wish to. You need assets
that can be deployed. You need assets on
social media. Hundreds maybe thousands
of accounts that push forth the Indian
narrative or whatever narrative warfare
we want to fight. You need accounts on
Twitter. You need hundreds of YouTube
channels that do the same thing in
shorts and all that Instagram accounts.
And you need big media outlets that put
forth a narrative. And now who whose job
is it to create this infrastructure? Is
it my job? I am one person. I can run
one channel. H is it the job of the of
the average common man and woman of
India? This
amorphous entity or is it the job of the
government of India to create this this
sharpedge uh sword that will you know
lead from the forefront in information
warfare? It's the government's job to
create this. The the the Chinese have
created this infrastructure. They have
so many channels, distribution outlets
all over social media, whether it is
Instagram, whether it's um whether it is
um YouTube, whether it is Facebook,
whether it is whatever else, whether
it's Twitter, they have their own big
media outlets like see like what Global
Times and CCTN and whatnot. They have
invested in these things. We have
completely failed. Our government has
completely failed to invest in these
things. The Chinese have the what the
the 10- cent uh army or whatever they
call it 20 cent or two cent army. I
don't know what it's called, but you
know a a paid army of
bots that you know just create this
noise, this pro-China noise and attack
anybody who's anti-China all over social
media. Why hasn't India invested in
this? Like you say, perception matters.
the government is supposed to do that.
The government has essentially unlimited
funds at its disposal is India's image
not important. So this is a failing this
is something that the government of
India has failed to do. Right? This is a
loss. This is something they should have
done and they have not done. So it's
unfortunate and it's disappointing.
Ryik says, "Can AI reach us? Can AI help
us reach type one civilization by 2100?"
A type one civilization on the Kardashev
scale is a civilization that controls
the entire energy and and resources of
its home planet. Can AI reach us? Can AI
help us reach that stage by 2100? AI can
help us reach pretty close to that. That
would mean that the entire planet
becomes uh you know gets plundered for
resources. Think about it. It's not a
very nice thought. The entire planet
becomes just gigantic resource.
Everything is plundered. Everything is
deconstructed. Every every square
kilometer of of the land is is exploited
or mined in some way. Uh well AI can re
can help us reach that definitely by
2100 or or get us very close to it for
sure. Kanesh Koshik says most of my
generation Gen Z is unaware or
unbothered about what's happening in
Indian history. the the the uh
distortions and all that. Firstly, how
can I contribute in solving this issue?
Secondly, solution of skill gap crisis
in jobs. Third, how can we force
government to reform education? And
thank you. Okay, multiple questions in
one, what can you contribute in solving
this issue? for well if you want to
solve the issue of the of the uh
distortions that exist in history and
what that thing then you have to become
a historian and and create the you know
put forth the correct picture uh without
being an expert in the field there's not
not much you can do except for you know
uh amplifying on social media and
elsewhere what uh good historians are
already doing. So right now historically
we only had the bad historians who had
any kind of uh exposure. Everybody else
was marginalized. We had great
historians and and scholars like Dr. BB
Lal who were completely sidelined
marginalized. Right? But today in the
age of social media it's impossible to
marginalize anybody as long as
sufficient numbers of people stand with
their right voice. So what you can do if
you're not an expert is amplify the
voices of the historians who are who are
trying to set the narrative right. Okay.
and and trying to uh portray the correct
u version of what happened in our
history and our history is very very
vast goes back 10,000 years. So there
are lots of different persons people
with historians who are working on
different facets and different aspects
and different eras of our history. So as
a as a non-expert you can amplify that
on social media you know uh but if you
really want to make a significant dent
significant impact then you have to
become an expert and do your own
original research. uh secondly solution
of skill gap crisis in jobs like I've
said a million times we have to reform
the education system why do we have so
many unskilled people in India people
with degrees you know master degree and
whatn not but when they get into a job
they have absolutely no skills they're
clueless and they have to be trained as
if they are starting from zero it's
because of the rotten education system
that we have and I have spoken about
this at length and I need to write about
this so uh the solution is complete re
reformation of the education system and
Nothing has been done about that. Uh how
can we force government to reform the
education system? Well, we can shout
from the rooftops and shout from the
treetops. Uh beyond that there's nothing
much we can do as an ordinary people
because well the government doesn't
listen to people uh you know who say I
mean the government only listens to to
certain classes of
people. That's the that's how it works.
Unless you have a street veto nobody
listens to you in India. So I'm not
asking anybody to go on the streets and
do anything like that. That's that
totally wrong. We don't do such things.
How do we force government to reform
education? I think only uh you know mass
movement can do it. If all of us unite
and refuse to go to school, refuse to go
to college, refuse to go to university,
we will not go anymore until you reform
the education system. Complete strike
like you know let's use Mr. Gandhi's
methods. They actually can work. You
know Mr. Gandhi's methods of Satagraha.
They're supposed to be used not against
foreign occupiers but against when you
need to have change in your country in a
civilized way. So yeah, let's let's do
satiyagra. Let's everybody you know
instead of jail brow should have school
cho everybody go you know refuse to
attend classes because the education
system is rotten. This can this can only
happen if there is unity but there isn't
that right. So that's you know Mr.
Gandhi's methods can use in can be used
in in certain scenarios where you don't
want to fight your government but you
want to tell the government that what
that c certain things need to be done in
that case you can use the method of
satyagraha so Mr. Kand did give us some
good tools but he used them against the
people who were occupying India non he
used them nonviolently and satag is
supposed to be a nonviolent tool. So
yeah that's that's a thought that's a
thought. Rahul Lakmanan says first of
all everybody thank you so much for the
contributions to to the channel it'll
really help. So Rahul says, "Does India
have a long-term vision for mining the
asteroids for minerals and metals?" As
of now, whatever when he hears about the
long-term plans for ISRO, uh there is
nothing about mining asteroids, asteroid
mining or such. As of now, uh the plans
that we have are as follows. We're going
to have a space station in orbit
sometime by the 2030s. Uh sometime this
decade, maybe in a year or two, we're
going to have the first Indian uh space
flights, human human space flights. So,
we're going to have Indian astronauts in
orbit. Eventually, we're going to have a
space station where Indian astronauts
can stay in orbit for an extended period
of time, right? Uh, by about 2040, we're
going to have a Chandrean mission that
will land humans on the moon, Indian
humans on the moon. And that's as far as
I can see that the plans are. Uh, we
don't have we don't seem to have plans
beyond that. If the plans exist, they
have not been put out in public, right?
Uh but I don't think anybody whether
it's NASA or SpaceX or whoever else has
a clear road map for starting asteroid
mining because astronaut mining is
something that's far in the future. The
asteroid belt is millions of kilometers
away. It's way way far away. It's
between the orbits of Mars and Jupiter.
The furthest anybody has concretely
planned thus far is simply reaching Mars
which is Elon Musk and Space X. But the
asteroid belt is beyond the orbit of
Mars. It's between the orbits of Mars
and Jupiter. And it's not like you have
millions of asteroids right in front of
you. It's empty
space. There are millions of kilometers
of distance between any two any any two
asteroids. So yeah, asteroid mining is
going to be very difficult. It's it's
something we we shouldn't even bother to
think about for 100 years unless there
are gargantuual gargantuan leaps in in
technology. So yeah, as of now we don't
have that. Feminist Slayer says, "If
humans can't survive on Earth, a
habitable planet due to
overexloitation, how could they possibly
expect to survive on the more hostile
Mars
instead?" The plan is simple. We exploit
and plunder the planet Earth. Then we
move on to Mars and do the same thing
there. And then we become a planet
hopping civilization. We go to a planet,
we plunder, exploit it. Then we go to
another planet, we do the same thing
there. And that sort of thing. That's
the that's the western way of doing
things. That's what they they have been
doing for the past 500 years ever since
they became the dominant force on the
planet. It's a civilizational and
cultural thing. The western worldview,
the Abrahamic worldview is that the
planet is a resource to be extracted.
Everything on the planet is a resource
for our enjoyment. It exists for our
enjoyment and our yeah for for our use.
So plunder the planet, plunder earth.
Once it becomes
uninhabitable, go to Mars eventually set
up a big population there. You plunder
that planet also. Then you move on move
on somewhere else. Maybe you will
terraform Venus in the next 1,000 years.
Maybe in the meanwhile you will
completely industrialize the moon and in
30 years time when people look at the
moon you will see lights all over all
over the
place. So that's not a good viable
strategy but it's it's a cultural thing.
It's a civilizational thing and the
western civilization culture is that of
exploitation and
plunder. Uh that's why it's important
for India to be a major player in the
space exploration sector because
otherwise it's going to be just
exploitation all over and over
again. Strike 47. Thank you so so much
sir for okay what's the question? I
recently saw Dr. Ranganatan's talk about
how Israel helped us during car and the
poke run tests. uh do they find us to be
good friends? There are no friendships
in geopolitics but uh India is a
valuable u partner to have for a nation
like Israel and for India also Israel is
a valuable partner to have because both
nations have a lot to offer to each
other right uh so look any help that is
given is not help it's an investment for
the
future and it's not like the help
doesn't come at a price right if you if
you if x if ex nation during wartime is
is selling us so and so arms,
ammunition, weapons. They are selling it
to us. They're not giving it for free.
So, it's a sale. It's a transaction.
It's a business transaction, commercial
transaction. But you know, certain
nations will refuse to do commercial
transactions with you. They'll say we
won't give you give you give you what
you need. So in that case so so Israel
definitely did the commercial
transactions and they sold us various uh
ammunition etc whatever during the k car
k car k car k car k car k car k car k
car k car k car kgill war and it was
good for us I don't know about the
pokran test but during the cargill war
definitely we were buying arms and
ammunition whatever it was from Israel
so Israel is a good partner to have for
India India is a good partner to have
for Israel we are we have a lot of
synergy there's a lot of convergence of
strategic interests, national interests.
There's a lot of u
um cooperation that's happening in the
defense field etc. So it's it's a good
partnership for us. Okay. But please
understand in geopolitics there's no
such thing as friendship. It's all
partnerships and you can have alliances
as well. Uh but it only happens it only
works when there is a significant
convergence of interests of both the
nations. If both the nations have very
similar interests then it makes sense
obviously logically for these two
nations to work together wherever the
interests align. So that's the case uh
that we have between India and
Israel. Prahab says do the theories of
Einstein prove that the future is
predefined? Does that prove that free
will doesn't exist? It's not Einstein's
theories that that could possibly raise
this question of whether the future is
predefined or not. So it's very sim
simple
uh it's it's Einstein's theories. What
are Einstein's theories? It's the theory
of relativity, general relativity and
special relativity. And according to
general relativity, gravitation, the
force that we the so-called force of
gravitation, it's nothing but the
curvature of spaceime. The presence of
mass tells spacetime how to curve and
the curvature of spacetime tells mass
how to move. So that kind of looks like
you know it it kind of predetermines how
things will happen on the grandest
scale. But Einstein also is one of the
pioneers and founders of the quantum
theory quantum mechanics quantum quantum
field theory eventually which which it
became and in quantum mechanics there is
indeterminacy right there is the the the
fact that uh there is randomness in
nature
uh nature is random nature is non-local
nature is shockingly counterintuitive
and we don't quite understand quantum
mechanics we we know how to use it but
we don't quite quite understand what it
means and what it's telling us. But so
so there is something called u quantum
fluctuations which arise out of quantum
randomness completely random events at
the very smallest scale of the universe.
But if you look at the big picture to
understand about pred whether something
is predetermined or not. See today we
have a certain kind of universe and we
know that the universe is expanding
right and we know that the universe has
a certain temperature. the CMBBR
temperature cosmic microwave background
radiation temperature and we know that
in the past therefore the universe must
have been much smaller. So if we run the
clock backwards we can see that
everything goes back to a single point
from which the universe expanded. That's
the big bang theory. So if everything
expanded out of a single point and we
know all the particles that exist in the
universe then these particles follow
very very straightforward laws laws that
are governed by differential equations.
If you take the randomness factor out of
it then it looks like everything is
predetermined and the randomness is
genuinely random. So you can't you know
predict that randomness but beyond that
everything seems to be predetermined. So
it looks like super determinism is a
thing and if if that is the case then
there is no such thing as free will and
what I'm saying right now has been
determined 13.8 billion years ago
essentially. So that's a scary thought
isn't it? But it's still a work in
progress. Okay we don't have a final
answer for sure.
Sergeant Skylon says we have reached a
$4 trillion economy, but will we fall
into the middle income economy? If so,
what can we do to fix it? So, we are now
roughly $4.5 trillion as an economy.
That's the annual GDP that we have. We
have surpassed Japan. So, we are the
fourth largest economy now and in a
reasonably short time we will surpass
Germany as well and we'll become the
third largest economy. That is that is
written. You can say that is that is
fated. But then
what? Then what? So if we become a $5
trillion economy, let's say in the next
one or two years, then the per capita
GDP of India will be still a very low
per capita GDP. So it's not even a
middle- inome economy. It's a low
reasonably low income economy. But let's
say we reach the $10 trillion mark in
the next 5 years, 10 years, whenever it
happens, hopefully 5 years, then we
become kind of a middle income economy.
Kind of low middle income or middle
income. But we want to become a high-
income economy, right? That's the great
dream. How do we fix it? The only way to
do it is through by becoming a
manufacturing power, a major
manufacturing power. For that, a lot of
reforms have to be done. Uh we need a
lot of foreign investment. There are a
lot of you know rich wealthy investors
and nations out there who would love to
invest in India. Set up shop in India,
set up manufacturing plants in India.
Everybody is looking to for for an
alternative to China, especially the
western nations. The only uh nation that
can do that at scale replace China is
India. So we have to the government
needs to
reform the the economy. It needs to make
the ease you know we need better ease of
doing business. We need to roll out the
red carpet for investors and on and so
on so forth. A lot of things need to be
done. So the only way we'll become more
than middle- inome economy is is if we
become a real manufacturing superpower.
It's certainly doable. uh we have the
demographics for it. We have all we have
all the conditions that you need for
becoming a manufacturing great power
superpower. So the government needs to
make sure that this happens smoothly and
there are no unnecessary obstacles in
the way. If that happens then we can
definitely become a middle- inome
economy soon. Right now we are not a
middle income economy. We are a low
income economy. The GDP per capita of
India is is abysmal. Okay. So yeah the
first step is to become a middle income
economy. then we'll think about becoming
a high income economy which is very
difficult unless unless you steal
everybody's wealth that's what the west
has done the reason the west is a high
income economy that these nations is
because they have plundered everybody
else's wealth and reduced everybody to
abject poverty in the past 500 years
don't look at the past 50 years 70 years
look at the past 500 years then you
understand what happened that's why they
are high income economies because they
took all the wealth everybody else had
earned over hundreds thousands of years
and stole it all
Right. We don't want to do that.
Hopefully, I
guess. Shubam says, "If you can go back
in time and change any three events in
Indian or world history, what which
events would you choose?" Well,
well, okay. That's that's an interesting
question.
Um, what would I do? That's a great
question. What what would I do for first
of all during the period of time when
the Turk invasions happened I would
ensure that there was a a major Indian
empire in power in India maybe prolong
the reign of the Gupta Empire by another
500 years that would indic that that
would mean that by the time the Turk
invasions happened at that time the
Gupta Empire would still be strong and
powerful and we have a united
subcontinent in which case the Arabic
and Turk invasions would have been
crushed.
absolutely utterly crushed. So that's
one thing I would change. Uh failing
that I would second thing I would I
would
change in more recent history is I would
ensure the Marata Empire doesn't crumble
because of
infighting. Right? The British did not
destroy the Mughal Empire. They
destroyed the Marata Empire. We already
had Hinduis Swaraja in India. We already
had reestablished a civilization state.
The British destroyed it. They did not
destroy the Mughal Empire. They
destroyed the Marata Empire. So what I
would have what I would change if I
could if I had the power is I would
ensure the Marata Empire did not suffer
from all the infighting. It remained
strong. It had a strong leadership and
that way the British and hopefully they
would have the wisdom to kick the
British out. We don't need you over
here. Get the hell out. That's the
second thing I would change. What's the
third thing I would change? I would make
the Indian
uh the Indian rebellion of 1946
succeed which means that we would have a
military government in power in 1946 and
we would they would have kicked the
British out through force. That way all
the all the all the British appointed
puppets who came to power after 1947,
they would never come to power. They
would have a military government, a
military dictatorship perhaps. And let's
see how it goes. Let's see how it goes.
I'm sure they were all well motivated
people the ones who tried to you know
revolt against the British the Indian
naval revolt and then it could have
become a bigger revolt if the Indian
armed forces had had come to know what
was happening but yeah it was foiled by
Mr. Gandhi and and his minions. So
that's another thing I would change. So
that's three events
hopefully. Okay. Hershett says, "Did the
Modi government kill leaders in Lakshad
to develop it for
tourism? If not, what's the news earlier
about local leaders being killed?" I
have heard no such news
whatsoever. Kill leaders in Lakshwep to
develop it for it for tourism. I'm
sorry. I have absolutely no idea. This
is the first time I'm ever hearing of
something like this. I don't think we in
India do such thing things. Kill leaders
to develop a place for
tourism. Um, no I I I have never heard
of heard of this which means that it is
most likely untrue whatever you may have
heard. I have not heard of it for sure
and that's not how the Modi government
operates at
all. Uh, Prohit thank you so much. Thank
you so much for your contribution. I
really appreciate it and I really
appreciate your viewership all of you.
Thank
you. Mr. Aiator says why didn't China
target the siliguri corridor in 1962?
The siliguri
corridor maybe at that time they just
wanted to humiliate India. See 1962 um
at that time India was under the
leadership of the great magnificent Mr.
Neu was positioning himself as a great
world statesman greater than everybody
else in the world because he could
lecture the world about what was right
and what what was wrong and so on and
Maetung was really really annoyed with
Mr. Nu for whatever reason Mr. Maetung
thought that maybe he should be more
magnificent than Mr. Nu so I think Mr.
Maatung wanted to teach the great
magnificent Mr. Javal Neu and lesson by
humiliating him by taking bits and
pieces of Indian territory and annexing
that. So once that was done once uh you
know the Chinese made inroads and then
they stepped back and they just grabbed
some territory the humiliation was done.
I think the objective of of the 1962 war
for China was to was to inflict a
military defeat on India which would be
a humiliation for India on the
international stage and after that the
world would not take Mr. hero and India
seriously anymore and I think they
achieved that. So just a little bit of
territorial gain is sufficient to
achieve that objective. They didn't want
to completely balconize India, break
India and so on so forth at that point
in time. Later on Chinese generals and
military uh thinkers have written
articles about the the need for China to
balconize India and so on. They've done
that later. Uh but Mahatong's objective
was not to balconize India. was simply
to essentially inflict a military and
political defeat on India and to
humiliate Mr. the great magnificent Mr.
Nu and I think he succeeded at that. So
that's why they didn't target the
Siliguri corridor. Yash Sahu says day by
day my belief in the Indian judiciary is
declining. Why is it starting to feel
more biased? What should be done to what
should be needed to make the Indian
judiciary more fair and transparent? Uh
look
uh in any democracy every single
institution in the nation needs to come
under the complete purview of the will
of the people right which means that uh
if if judicial appointments are done
they should uh be under the uh control
and review of the people's elected
officials. So I think currently that say
that state doesn't exist for whatever
reason for historical reasons. Uh and
that's why obviously one can understand
that uh many Indians would feel that
there are issues with this uh particular
institution. So what needs to be done I
would say is for the government to take
this up. The government of India the
central government they are our elected
representatives. It is for them to take
the necessary actions to ensure that
everything is as per the standards we
expect in a fully functional and
highquality democracy. So I think
whatever reforms need to happen in the
judicial domain uh those need to be
thought through by the government and
there's not those need to be implemented
and deployed step by step. I think
attempts were done in the past and maybe
did not work out but you know I'm sure
the government of India has the people's
mandate to carry out whatever reforms
are uh required. So I would leave it to
the government of India to do what is
right and do it do it as per you know in
in
in a pred in a properly defined time
frame not something that goes on
forever. Uh remnants to revival thank
you so much for your contri contribution
appreciate it. Thank you. Rahul says,
"What happened during operation
cahuta?" Operation Kahuta. Now, what on
earth is that? Kahuta is a nuclear
facility in Pakistan, isn't it? Uh, I
don't know. So, let me try and Google
Operation
Cahuta. What is Operation Cahuda? Let's
see. So, here we have our friend Google
Operation
Ca
Cahoot. What is that? a clandestine
operation program undertaken by
Pakistan. Okay. The Pakistan nuclear
weapons development program. It was
called the Cahuta project.
Okay. So what
happened? Okay. So let's not go into
this. I understand what operation Kahuta
is. The the Pakistani program to develop
nuclear weapons. Look what really
happened. We don't we're not quite sure.
But eventually they ended up with
nuclear weapons.
So
uh Zulfikar Ali Bh had had promised had
had made this this this uh commitment to
himself and to his people of Pakistan
that Pakistan will anyhow develop a
nuclear weapon after India's 1974 test
in
pokist said that you know it doesn't
matter if you have to eat grass but we
will deploy all of our resources in in
acquiring in developing nuclear weapons
and then they started this nuclear
weapons program. And in the 1980s, India
and Israel wanted to
destroy their nuclear
reactor and Israel had chocked out a
plan to to deploy the Israeli air force
from Indian air bases and then Indian
and Israeli aircraft would take off
together and destroy the Pakistani
reactor. But at the last moment, Israel
somehow pulled out of it for I don't
know what reason. Now the question is
you have to understand that Israel is
America's number one ally. Israeli is
the United States number one ally and
Pakistan was a very prominent US vasal
state in the 1980s. So was there an
American angle which made the Israelis
pull out of the of the of the plan to
destroy the the Pakistani nuclear base?
Was was an assurance or a commitment
given to Israel that Pakistan would
never use nukes against Israel? Is there
a secret understanding between Pakistan
and Israel? That's the question. We
don't know the answers to that. But
eventually it is said that a Pakistani
nuclear physicist called Abdul Kadr
Khan, Dr. Abdul Kadrh Khan Khan, he
stole some blueprints of centrifuges or
whatever for the Netherlands or
somewhere in Europe and brought them to
Pakistan and that's how the Pakistanis
were able to acquire nuclear weapons. It
is also alleged that maybe the Chinese
provided them nuclear weapons technology
or maybe these nuclear weapons that the
chi that the Pakistanis have maybe these
nuclear weapons are American nuclear
weapons. We don't know what quite what
the truth is. A nation like Pakistan, a
low tech primitive nation like Pakistan,
it's very hard to imagine that nation
being able to develop nuclear weapons on
its own or even with foreign help. Most
likely these are nuclear weapons donated
by either China or the
US. Okay, that's what I think happened.
So I don't think this operation cahuta
to to develop Pakistani nuclear weapons
was successful. I don't think if there
have any scientists or engineers who are
capable of doing this. Most likely the
nuclear weapons were donated to
Pakistan to serve you know to serve a
certain purpose. I would say my money
would be more on the Americans than the
Pakistanis. So most likely in my opinion
I have no evidence to back it up. It is
just a hunch. Okay. I think the
Pakistanis never were able to develop
nuclear weapons. I think most likely the
Americans or otherwise the Chinese
donated a few nuclear weapons to
Pakistan and that's what Pakistan has
been storing in its whatever places you
know nuclear storage sites I think it's
most likely the Americans so so that is
what I think happened this operation
kahut I think it's just a eyewash
uh RC says what's my thought on the
potency of palant anduril these are two
terms from the lord of the rings the
palant was that seeing stone and was the
sword sword sword of of of
ofur or something but these are now
weapons systems so let me just Google
what is palant what's I think there is
some uh networkcentric warfare component
AI component so what is palant palant
oops what is palantier palant
technologies what does it do software
platforms for big data analytics but
obviously there's a military military
angle to it artificial intelligence
platform and so on. Must be pretty good
if the Americans are investing so much
in it. And what's
Andural, Andural. So that's
uh defense, autonomous systems. Okay.
Artificial intelligence and robotics.
Look, the Americans are at the forefront
of these technologies, whether it's AI,
whether it's robotics, whether it's
networkcentric warfare, all that. So I'm
sure these are pretty potent. Pretty
potent but we haven't not we have not
seen them um deployed in actual war thus
far as far as I know but I'm sure the
technology is great. Brianka Biswas
thank you so much
sir. Meet thank you sir. I'm passionate
about ge geopolitics geioeconomics and
international affairs. How can I build a
career in this field in Canada or India?
Well, how do you build a career in
geopolitics, geioeconomics or
international affairs? You can have a
career in media for example in which if
you are an expert in these fields, you
can be a an a prominent analyst in
media. The second thing you can do is uh
you can build a career as an
academic if you're an expert in
geopolitics, geopconomics, geost
strategy, international affairs. So you
can be a professor or a lecturer or
something. That's another thing you can
do. What else can you do? You can start
a think tank that offers very
specialized niche services to companies
and corporations. Geostrategic
consulting. So essentially what's the
risk exposure of the company? What's the
geopolitical risk exposure that the
company is currently uh uh you know
facing and how to mitigate those risks?
What are the what are the actions you
can the company can take to mitigate the
risks? How to spread the risks and hedge
your bets and all that? uh what are the
supply chains that the company uses that
could be impacted by geopolitical
developments all of that sort of thing
that's called geopolitic geostrategic
risk consulting that's one thing you
could do so you could have a think tank
or a company uh that can offer such
services otherwise you can be part of a
government and be a geostrategist which
means an adviser a policy adviser a
strategic adviser to the government to
let's say the military or the ministry
of external affairs or foreign ministry
ministry of state of state or whatever
of the of the country and if you are
high quality expert they will you know
have you as a consultant or as an as a
strategic adviser and you can then shape
foreign policy. So these are the
different ways in which you can build a
career in
geopolitics/geeoconomics and
international affairs in either Canada
or India. Now Canada uh I think India is
more and more relevant in geopolitics
geostrategy. Um, so in India, if you
were there, you could either be in the
media or hopefully if you're really
good, you could be in the government or
you could be in academia, even though
India's academic system is rotten. If
you're in Canada, you could probably be
an adviser to the government or be in
academia, have a think tank or a or or
or or a firm that that is a risk
advisory firm, geostrategic risk
advisory firm and so on. So these are
various things, various options you can
explore. if you want to build a career
in geopolitics, geocconomics,
geostrategy, international affairs, etc.
All right, all the best
sir. Uh, Shubam says, "Kiwa from Japan."
Kiwas,
uh, if I if you get a chance to ask
three questions to a time traveler from
the year 2100, what questions are you
asking?
Fascinating. What the questions I
ask? So first of all I would ask uh
who's ruling the world? Is it an
individual? Is it an entity? Is it a
country? Is it uh a kingdom? Is it an
empire? Who's ruling the world? Who are
the which are the major powers in 2100?
That's one question I would ask.
Secondly, I would ask what's the
population of the planet
planet and uh what's the forest cover?
What's the what's the biomass like? Is
it all you know cattle or is it all is
it more wild animals? What's the balance
like biomass? Uh I would ask uh what are
the technologies that are prevalent? How
far has the human species spread? Are we
still confined to earth or have we
colonized the moon? Have we colonized
Mars? Have we have we ventured out
further into space? What's the further
human beings have traveled? Then I would
ask what are the latest advances in
physics? Right? Have we been able to
quantize gravity? Have we been able to
figure out whether gravity is a force or
it is is it's entirely something else.
And uh yeah, gravity is the big question
today. Nobody has been able to figure
out what gravity is. We are at the same
place where we are today in 2025 that we
were in the year 2000. No progress
whatsoever in gravity. So have we
breached breached that big brick wall
that that is has caused the stagnation
of the field of physics since
1979? These are some of the questions I
would ask. I'm sure I would have many
more questions as well. Uh but yes, I
think I've exceeded your quot of three
questions. So I'll I'll stop there. But
yeah, that's the kind of questions I
would have. I'm I'm sure I would have a
lot of other
questions. Zishan, thank you sir.
Xiinping's hair is clearly starting to
turn gray since he has been purging the
CCP for 10 years. How do you think his
succession will go? Is there a plan for
Mr. Xiin Jinping's succession? Look, Mr.
Xiinping is in his is in his 19 is in
his 70s. So obviously his hair, it's no
surprise that his hair is turning gray,
right? Many people who are much younger
have their hair turning gray. I mean,
for example, look at me. I'm in my late
40s. But so
u so he has been purging the CCP for 10
years. What he's been doing, he has been
consolidating power. Okay. If you want
to be in power for a long time, you have
to ensure that there are no potential
uh
challenggers in in the frey or around
you or in the Chinese Communist Party or
on the horizon. You have to identify
every possible potential
challenger and eliminate those. That's
how it goes, you know. Uh and that's the
that's the way the game is played in the
Chinese Communist Party. It's a very
very tough world, the Chinese Communist
Party. only the toughest rise and even
in out of those that even the those who
are even tougher they are the ones who
actually survive and thrive in the
Chinese Communist Party system. So if
you want to rise in the CCP, you have to
really perform at every stage of the
game at every level. Whether it's at the
the village level, then the district
level, the city level, the state, the
province level, eventually the central
level, you have to really perform and
you have to out compete and outperform
everybody else. And there's intense
competition for promotions and and and
you know, rising in status in the
Chinese Communist Party, rising in
status, rising in power. So it's a very
tough game. It's completely
meritocratic. It's only about merit. Of
course, there will be some family
connections and all that also that game
is also played. You have the so-called
princlings, young princes or whatever
they called, you know, the second
generation of the Chinese Communist
Party uh leadership and so on. So, there
are nepotism games as well. But overall,
it's mainly
uh it's to a very large extent pretty
meritocratic. So if somebody rises to
the top position, that person has risen
by eliminating all threats, opposition
and so on. There's going to be a big
body count behind that person
figuratively speaking, not literally
speaking, maybe perhaps also literally.
Um so Mr. Xiinping has consolidated his
hold in the Chinese Communist Party. He
ensured there are that he is surrounded
by people who are entirely utterly
completely loyal to him. He has
eliminated all all challengers. But now
he is in his 70s
maybe. What's his age? 7374. Let's
quickly Google it. What is Mr.
Xiinping's age? I am assuming 7374 or
something like that. Xi Jinping age.
Okay. 71. So he is in his early 70s. So
one could safely assume that he'll be in
power maybe for the best part of the
next decade. Yeah. But eventually
there's going to be a succession because
eventually once you start reaching the
80s you know you are no longer where you
used to be when you were in your 60s and
70s mental mentally and stamina wise
physical health-wise. So you have to
eventually hand over to a
successor. How will the succession go?
That's a big question mark. We don't
know who could be the successor. I'm
sure he must have thought he must have
already thought at this point in time of
several potential successors. at that
level you have to make all the
contingency plans because you never know
what will happen tomorrow right so I'm
sure he has made some kind of plan for
the transition of power succession and
uh if the succession goes well and the
next person to come to power is is
equally good or better then China will
do great right that's always the
critical phase in in in an empire or a
kingdom's history the succession between
one leader and another. If the suction
succession goes right and a good leader
comes to power as the next person, a
strong leader, then the empire thrives.
But if a weak person comes to
power, if an undeserving person comes to
power, then all hell breaks loose and
the empire crumbles. We have seen this
over and over again. The transition of
power, the succession is the most
critical phase. So um from a Chinese
perspective the Chinese people will be
hoping that the succession goes well and
for us we will wait and watch what else
can we say because the system is so
opaque we can't really really tell
what's happening and who could be the
potential two three people who could be
chosen for potential for being potential
successors we can't say from here we
can't even say for Russia who could be
the next next in line after Mr. Putin.
So let's wait and
watch. Remnants to revival says Indian
origin student getting suspended from
MIT. Okay, that's news for me. I think
there's a lot happening in the US uh
education academic field. It's going to
be really difficult going forward. It
looks like for Indians to study in the
US. Uh and it's a great opportunity in
that case for India to to offer better
alternatives to students in India. But
for that we have to reform the education
system not apply band-aids on shortgun
wounds. So
yeah, Sudesh's financial consultancy
says recently PM Modi addressed rising
northeast investors
summit. What are the benefits or aids
the government is providing? Can you
guide? I am not aware. I have not seen
his address to the rising northeast
investors summit. Uh and I have not read
any of the documentation so I don't
know. But look the northeast, the far
east of India. Let's put that on the
map. It's it's it's critical. It's a
very important part of India. It's it's
something that's very important. We need
this region to be stabilized and we need
this region to develop. We need the
people of this region to be prosperous
and happy. So we are talking about
obviously this region which starts with
Assam
Megallay and uh we have the other states
of Arunach Pradesh, Nagaland, Manipur,
uh Tripura and Nisuram in this region
that's the so-called northeast. is
actually the Indian far east and it's
our gateway to Southeast Asia and this
region is geographically actually
located within Southeast Asia and uh we
would like to see it's very important
for the country that this region does
well uh the people are prosperous there
is economic growth there are economic
opportunities there are de developmental
opportunities there are entrepreneurial
opportunities there are opportunities
for the people who live in this region
to to better their life to have better
financial status because the region has
been historically very badly mistreated.
Even today there are lots of you know
disastrous things happening there for
especially the cookie invasion of
Manipur is a huge huge challenge for
India's sovereignty and territorial
integrity project K which was started by
the Biden administration the project to
create a new nation artificial nation
cookie land for Christ that is a huge
challenge to India sovereignty and
that's something we are still grappling
with um so when you have a northeast
investor
summit it can be pretty much guaranteed
that Manipur is currently not part of
the equation because Manipur is in
chaos. Um so I'm not sure what the
benefits and AIDS would be. I'm sure
there would be maybe you may get loans
at preferential rates. Maybe you will
get loans where earlier you could not
get loans. Um maybe some other guidance
or or other thing be given to small-time
entrepreneurs and so on. That's what I
can imagine but I'm not quite sure what
the actual uh details are because I've
not looked into it. But what I can say
is that the far east of India is a
critical area. It's a critical
geographical part of India and we need
to ensure uh and there are lots of
foreign eyes on the region. Whether it's
China, whether it is East Pakistan,
Bangladesh, whether it's the US,
everybody is everybody wants to meddle
in the region and destabilize the
region.
See after the Afghan Taliban um they
banned poppy cultivation in Afghanistan
banned the use you know cultivation of
drugs in Afghanistan there was a sudden
upsurge in poet plantations in
Manipur and uh you know so all this
needs to be taken care of and the
foreign influx into Manipur needs to be
ended and so on so it's a very important
region and I I hope it prospers long
term
really now says with due respect did the
CDS fumble with due respect I am I find
it incomprehensible what he did what was
the need for this chief of defense staff
to give an interview to Bloomberg to the
western media what's the need to give an
interview to the white man and justify
our position or or or give any
statements why why I don't get it and
then whatever he said it's even more
incomprehensible did he did he fumble
It looks like he did unless there were
directions from from up top somewhere to
go and do this which I just don't
understand. My simple question is
this. Every single action taken by
people at this level has to directly
serve the Indian national interest. In
what way does this interview serve the
Indian national interest is my question.
I don't get it. So
yeah okay thank you sir ma'am I don't
know I don't know how to read this
sirillic it's been too long can you
please assess whether the right the rise
of the right wing in Europe will be a
good or a bad thing for India okay drag
all right got
it Europe is more and more irrelevant in
the world
today the European nations most of them
lack complete sovereignty
And they are not players in geopolitics.
They are players in geoeconomics because
Europe is still as as a whole the EU
region, the Shenhen region, it is one
composite economy and it's it's still a
significant economy but its economic
magnitude is declining. It's no longer
going to be the center of the world. So
the the rise of the right wing or
leftwing or whatever, it's a internal
European problem. is is not going to
have a long-term bearing on the
long-term future of the
world. And if right-wing governments
come to power or leftwing governments
stay in power, we going to deal with
them anyway in in the best possible way.
And we're going to tell them, look, we
don't care about your politics. Your
politics is your concern. It is none of
our business. And we will not
interfere in your internal politics. We
respect what you're doing and we respect
the sentiments of the people of your
country and they've elected you. So we
are very happy and and very pleased to
do business with you and that's all it's
going to be like. So whether it's
rightwing or leftwing we will seek to
have mutually beneficial cooperation
with them. So it it will not really
matter. See in Italy we have a
right-wing government. Madame Melani,
she is a right-wing politician and we
have great relations with with Italy
under Madame Melani. U Mu Mak in France
is a leftwing politician. We have
excellent relations with him and so on
and so forth. So it doesn't really
matter for us. Okay, we're going to have
relationships based on mutual interests
in which case it it's fine. In which
case the the local politics doesn't
matter really. now says Mahendra EV
would be 100% indie genus if not for HR
E S and lithium. I'm what is HR E S I'm
not quite sure what that is.
Um, shall I Google that? H R E S. Not
sure what you're saying, sir. But you
know, it helps if you don't use
abbreviations. H R E S. What is
that? Okay. Rare earth elements. Heavy
rare earth. Okay. Okay. You're talking
about r heavy rare rare earth elements.
Uh so the Mahindra electric vehicle
would be 100%.
Well, I think we need to start looking
for our own heavy rare earth elements.
We have a gigantic territorial area and
I'm sure we have rare earths, but maybe
we haven't done enough to look for them.
So, I think that's what we need to do,
right? We need to start looking for our
own rare earth minerals and elements
within India. Shivan, thank you so much,
sir. Appreciate it. Geopolitical Dub
says, will Trump achieve anything apart
from Nobel Prize? I don't think he's
going to get a Nobel Prize. He won't get
it.
And
uh what will he achieve? He's going to
achieve
more he's going to the the his actions
are going to result in more instability
in the world. He's rampaging around like
a drunk elephant, right? Isn't he? And
uh it's going to cause old alliances of
the U of the US to to become very shaky
alliances like NATO alliances like the
European Union and he's going to
alienate a lot of a lot of nations that
would otherwise have been long-term
partners for the US and a lot of
short-term
um players will seek to
gain short
quick wins and quick benefits from
the way he is going is going to be like
that. So, it looks like he's going to
end up doing way more harm than good to
the US and maybe it's by design. Maybe
they want to shake up the world order,
but I don't think he's going to achieve
anything the way he's going right now.
He's going to end up doing way more harm
than good, you know. Uh
yeah. Nandanda Kazor says, "What's the
relationship between the US and Israel?
What what is the history of the creation
of Israel? Was it created by certain
someone? Do they control the deep state?
What's the relationship between the
between the two
nations? The US regards Israel as its
number one ally and this is an ally that
you know there are no conditions here.
This is a unconditional alliance. So
it's a privileged relationship that
Israel enjoys with the US and no matter
what Israel does the US will support
Israel and stand by Israel. So that's
the relationship. Uh why is it like
that? I'm not quite sure but it is what
it is. What's the history of the
creation of Israel? Well, that's a very
long answer to give but you know Israel
was created um you know at the end of
let's say the second world war around
that time 4748 around that time uh the
process started long before that of
course you know this this land
historically if you go back 2,000 years
it belonged to the Jewish people 2 and a
half thousand years before the Assyrians
came and deported the Jews to various
parts of the world and then the Persians
came in and saved the Jews and so under
Kurush the Great, Cyrus the Great, long
history. We'll not go into that. But
after World War II, after the the the uh
after the events of the Second World War
and the persecution of the Jews by the
by the Nazis and so on, this nation was
eventually created and the moment it was
created, it went to war and so on. Uh
you had the initial war, but it survived
and it's been able to thrive mainly with
American and Western help and so on. Was
it created by a certain someone? I'm not
sure who the certain someone is, so I
don't know. Do they control the deep
state? Well, that's a good question and
we don't know, but it's possible. It's
possible. Sai Tja Reddi says, "How do
top chess grand masters calculate 30
plus moves ahead rapidly and can an
average person train themselves to
develop such similar deep calculation
abilities?" I think look first of all if
you want to be a chess chess grandmaster
many people want to do want to become
one but very few people are actually
able to achieve that right it's because
it's so incredibly hard it's very
difficult you need certain kinds of a
certain kind of mental framework and
mental makeup to be able to do this uh
so you need to obviously uh be super
intelligent and uh have great powers of
concentration and have a tremendous
memory to be able to do this. And then
what you do in chess is you study
patterns and you study openings and you
study end games and you study various uh
tactical maneuvers and so on and you
memorize them. Memorize as much as
possible and you just do it over and
over again. So the more you do it the
more you will able to retain. Typically
chess grand masters can mostly think 12
13 14 moves ahead. I'm not sure about 30
plus maybe it's possible maybe people
like Kasparov Anand um Karpov Kramnik
etc may be able to do that who's the
latest guy Magnos Carlson yes and so on
maybe the elite grand masters could
perhaps calculate 30 plus moves ahead uh
and the average person can try and
emulate that maybe the average person
can do five moves six moves ahead but
you know if the more you try the more
the better you get uh so the average
person can also use the same methods I'm
not sure you will get the same results
but it'll it'll certainly make you a
better thinker and uh it'll give you a
better amount you know better memory and
better reasoning power etc. So it's
certainly something if you want to do
you can try and follow similar
approaches like chess
training. Dashi Mukhadi. Thank you so
much. Thank you. Nandanda Kizor says how
does the world power center work? The
few powerful people only control US or
do they have their arms into RIC2? Do we
control the RBI? Um look we don't know
right if if there is a small number of
people who control the world they have
done a great job of staying hidden
because we don't know their names we
don't know who they are there there is
speculation that they are the Illuminati
they are the whatever else but that's
all speculation there is zero hard
evidence you know one the one thing you
see
historically kingdoms and empires always
went out of their way to showcase their
instrument instruments of power, right?
That's how you showcased how how
glorious you were. So the Romans made
these great columns and made these great
monuments in which they, you know,
recorded all their all their victories
and the names of the of the of the great
people, great generals who who won the
victories and the names of the emperors
and so on. And the Persians did that.
Our our emperors did that. Our empires
did that. Whether it's the Moras or the
Kushans or the Guptas or the Chhatra the
Cholas or the Maratas or whoever we have
always glorified and and put the people
in power front and center right and show
showcase the instruments of power. The
Anglo-Saxons what they've
done is that they have all they have
sought to hide their instruments of
power and hide what they're actually
doing to stay in power. That way they
can do whatever they want but still they
can keep on harping on about human
rights and democracy and all that. So
when you have a system which tries to
hide its instruments of power and the
people who are in power that's when you
end up with a system like
this. So we don't know what the power
center is like. We don't know who the
people who may or may not be the real
people in power in charge who they are.
And uh since the US is the most most
powerful nation, maybe it looks like
they control that nation and by
extension its
was they have their arms into RA2,
Russia, India, China. Well, they would
love to have their tentacles deep inside
RA. Uh see, I think the Chinese got rid
of all their spies embedded within a
long time ago. Starting with the time
Mr. Xin came to power, they got they
identified and got rid of all the spies.
Maybe some still exist. The Russians
under Mr. Putin also have done that. I
think if you look at RA, India would
most likely be the most
compromised. Yeah. Do we control RBA? As
as far as we know, we
do. Anonymous says
Otto's podcast. I don't know what means.
Let me quickly see what Ottobo means.
OTBO. Ohio thoroughbred breeders and
owners. Okay. I don't know what it means
but whatever. Um, if I have to open a
tech
company then where should I build or
position my headquarters based on the 75
states map? Should I build multiple mini
headquarters across parat? It depends on
how much capital you can deploy and what
you're manufacturing and and you know
there's a reason why a company is
located in position X location X if not
instead of position Y or location zed.
What what's how do you decide where to
have the headquarters of your company?
It there are multiple factors that go
into this choice. If you're a
manufacturing company then you need to
be in a place where you know especially
your manufacturing plants need to be
where it's easy to access easy to get
the raw materials for the manufacturing.
If you are if you need a headquarters
then it should be ideally centrally
located where you know equidistant from
all the manufacturing uh plants so you
can you know have equal access to all of
them and of course it makes sense to be
in a financial hub where you get access
to all the financial services and so on
so forth and so on. So it depends if if
you're if you're a tech company, you
want to be in a place where you have
other tech companies because then you
have all the infrastructure and know
everything you need but a tech company
know needs a place like for example
Bangalore or Pune or or Hyderabad or
something you know these are the places
where you have lots of tech companies
because all the infrastructure you need
for tech companies is available there
easily. Uh so it makes sense if so and
if you were to build multiple mini
headquarters, imagine the the cost it
will how much it will cost you to to
either buy or or or rent all that all
you know the the office space and hire
people and have them there and so on. So
it makes sense to have just one
headquarters and in today's world you
can control everything virtually from
one one location. So there's no need to
build multiple mini headquarters. Makes
sense to have just one
headquarters. So that's
uh yeah that that makes more sense.
Rohan Surja, thank you so much. Thank
you very much sir. Really now says
government really left illegals in the
no man's land. Lol. It looks like the
government of India is now taking some
kind of action against the illegal
Bangladeshi infiltrators who are
squatting on our territory. It's a good
beginning and it should really really
really be taken to the next level
because we have maybe 100 million of
these cumulatively plus the Rohhingas
plus the cookies plus the Pakistanis
plus God knows who else. So it's high
time we do this whether you leave them
in no lands no man's land or you push
them properly into Bangladesh or or
whatever that's not our problem. We
don't want illegals on our territory
that's it. The best thing for the
illegals is to move out voluntarily
otherwise they will face whatever
consequences according to the law. So
I'm sure I'm I'm glad the government of
India is now finally taking some action.
I think it's it's a good beginning and I
congratulate and appreciate the
government of India and I thank the
government of India for starting the
process and please take it to its
logical conclusion. Please evict all of
them. I know it'll take a lot of time
maybe 2 three years perhaps hopefully. I
know it's a lot of effort but we the
country really needs this. Please,
please do
this. Prabhav says, "Please launch a
course to teach us physics in quantum
mechanics from the beginning. What's the
most mind-bending thought experiment you
have done?" Thought experiments. Thought
experiments you can do all kinds of
things. Launch a course to teach
physics. I mean, how many takers were
there? I I can do that certainly. But
let's say I spend 6 months and create a
whole course and record the whole thing
and create all the course materials and
then 20 people buy it because you know
nobody wants to there are very few
takers for physics courses. I would love
to do it. I would love nothing more than
doing this because this is what what
what I love the most. uh but after
spending all the time and effort if 20
people 50 people buy the course then you
know it's it's
like when you create a course it has to
be something that's highly in demand
that that will give that will provide
value to as many people as possible
that's the best way to use your time I
mean I would love to do physics live
streams every day I would love to do
that but you see me mainly talking about
geopolitics because it is most more
relevant to the lives of most people,
right? Uh most people don't care about
science. The doesn't affect their lives.
It's a very niche topic for most people.
Space exploration, quantum field theory,
or who cares about these things? So
that's why I don't talk about that much
these days. I don't do those live
streams anymore. Um so yeah, I would
love to do this. What's the mind most
mindbending thought experiment I have
done? Thought experiments. There are so
many of these. One of the interesting
thought experiments in quantum mechanics
is the delayed choice quantum eraser
experiment which kind of raises the
question of retro causality. Do things
that happen in the past sorry do things
that happen in the future have an have
an effect on the past? That sort of
thing. Delayed choice quantum eraser
experiment thought experiment. So
right. Uh Aries Manticor says does the
Western Empire have an expiration date?
Every empire has an expiration date, but
what the date is, we can't tell unless
we are fortune tellers or we are
superior geopolitical analysts or
geostrategists. Does the Western Empire
have an expiration date? As of now, I
can't see an expiration date. Uh if if
they uh win the AI race, then they could
have an expiration date which is in
excess of 1,000 years. you know, if they
win the AI race and they are the first
to develop artificial super
intelligence, they'll win the war. Then
nobody will be able to catch up with
them. Uh so yeah, right now the the fate
of the world is in the balance. Who's
going to win the AI race? That's going
to essentially determine the future of
who rules humanity.
Rohan Sunija says, "How can we solve
India's white labeling labeling program
like Indian companies buying foreign
goods and putting their label on it?"
Well, it is what it is. You know, it's
not
illegal. You can just have a Chinese
company manufacture whatever. You bring
it here, stamp your label on it and and
sell it. Who will know? And you get such
cheap uh products all over the place,
you know, whether you look at Flipkart
or Amazon or whatever, you see the same
product with different brands, different
branding, same thing. They're all, I'm
sure, manufactured in China, imported
here in in large quantities in big
scale. And then the local companies put
their label and market it as as if it's
something they made. So this will this
problem, how can it be solved? Firstly,
we have to stop the Chinese, prevent the
Chinese from dumping cheap products into
India by raising the trade and tariff
barriers. Secondly, we have to seriously
encourage make in
India, manufacturing in India.
Everything should should be manufactured
in India. So, if you first of all
prevent these things from coming into
India, then there'll be need for
manufacturing things in India. So, it
has to be a well-c calibrated approach,
well thought out, properly sequenced
approach.
uh so most of these things that come in
from China are not really necessities
right for us it's kind of luxuries and
nice to have items so those things you
can put higher tariffs from them on them
and whatever necessities may exist we
can consider
um allowing those to be imported from
China on a case by case basis so that's
one thing we can do and then we have to
do it make it really easy for Indian
businesses to do well in India ease of
doing business ease of manufacturing
cut down on the red tape, cut down on
the alleged corruption which allegedly
is allegedly everywhere and so on. All
those things if we can do then we can
solve these
problems. Vishal Nanta says what are
axion particles? Axons are a
hypothetical form of dark matter. These
are particles that interact. See our
regular particles like protons,
neutrons, electrons,
uh quarks and all the other particles of
the standard model zoo. All these
particles most of them they interact via
multiple forces. One is the strong
nuclear force. Second is the weak
nuclear
force. Third is u electromagnetism.
Fourth is gravity. Now when it comes to
the
electron, if you look at the proton, if
you look at the neutron, these all have
different forces that that uh uh they
interact via. Now when it comes to the
axion, it doesn't interact via the
electromagnetic force. It's a
hypothetical particle. The axion, this
hypothetical particle does not interact
via
electromagnetism. It doesn't interact
via the strong force. it only interacts
via the weak nuclear force and gravity.
So that's why they they are supposedly
so high so so so difficult to detect in
in that they they're kind of you know
similar to neutrinos you know from that
perspective because nutrinos they
interact only by the via the weak force
and they're very small mass almost
negligible gravitational interaction. So
axons if they exist they could be a
significant important uh it's a
component of dark matter it's a
candidate for it's a candidate particle
for the for dark matter but we have
never observed them so that's in brief
what
axons
are project smiling Buddha says are
mixed race children inferior lot of such
content on the internet that says so
like they have identity issues bad genes
etc you know most of This content comes
from white supremacists on the internet
h and because because on platforms like
Twitter etc they are given a lot of
prominence for some reason white
supremacist accounts that's why it
becomes that's why these these uh claims
become quite popular like race mixing is
inferior race mixing is bad the white
race is superior if if white if white
people may intermar with people from
other races then you are doing race
mixing and then the the the the
resulting human beings are of inferior
quality and so on. These are all white
supremacist
claims. And yeah, you are right. There's
a lot of content on the internet that
says so because these accounts are
somehow being pushed by X, you know,
being given special prominence by X. It
looks like that. uh what happens when
when people Okay. So what happens? First
of all, when you have children born of
two parents of the same so-called race,
it means that both the parents are quite
similar genetically. There's a lot of
genetic proximity between the parents.
Now we know that all human beings are
related to each other. We are all
distant cousins of each other. But when
it comes to Indians, we are much closely
closely related to each other compared
to let's say people from Africa or
people from Finland or people from uh
Botswana or people from
China. Indians are closer relatives of
each other than other nationalities or
let's say you take any two people from
Sweden or two people from Italy or
people from France. any two humans from
f France will be genetically much more
similar to each other than a French
person and let's say a German person or
a French person and a Russian person so
on so when you have two parents of the
same so-called ethnicity or race then it
means they are genetically similar and
the child will also be very genetically
similar to
them when you have people parents of two
different races so let's say a black
person and a white person or an Indian
and and a Japanese person or something
like that right then you have parents
who are genetically quite distant from
each
other. And when these two parents uh um
produce children, then the children will
uh inherit very different sets of genes.
And typically what that happens, what
happens is that the more distant the
parents are genetically, the stronger
the genetics of the off offspring is
going to be because it's going to be
able to pull from the best best genetics
of both parents.
So you know that the closer the parents
are, the more there is the chance of of
inbreeding, right? And genetic defects,
which tells you that the the more
distant genetically the parents are, the
the superior the children are going to
be from a long-term genetic perspective.
So it's not like they're going to have
bad genes. It means that they're going
to going to have stronger genes,
identity issues and all. Well, that's
that's a social sociological problem,
socioultural problem. And they may have
identity issues depending on the kind of
country you're living in. In the US,
everybody is race mixed. So who cares
about identity issues? There are no
identity issues. If you are in even in
in most European countries today, lot of
people are of mixed ethnicity because of
the ongoing social demographic
re-engineering program and so on. Uh so
I don't think in today's day and age
there's going to be identity issues and
this story about bad genetics that
that's complete fiction
unfortunately. Harardik Jooshi says
what's the possibility of World War II
given the global current global fiction
also will India achieve its economic
goals even if there is a regime change
right now hopefully the possibility of
World War II is remote and
distant. What could be the global
triggers right now for World War II?
What is what is my definition of World
War II? My definition of World War II is
nuclear nuclear exchange between major
nuclear powers. That's my definition of
World War II. Essentially, it means a
nuclear exchange between the US and
Russia. That's what World War II means.
India and Pakistan having a nuclear
exchange will only result in the
annihilation of one nation. It will not
cause a global war unless other nations
choose to step in which most likely
won't happen right India and China
having a nuclear exchange once again the
US won't get involved Russia most likely
won't get involved and we don't have
such large nuclear arsenal so it it
won't really uh destroy the world the
only scenario which destroys the world
is if the US and Russia go to war so
that is world war and today Ukraine
could be a flash point But Ukraine is
kind of being managed and there's always
some provocation and some kind of
escalation here and there but it's being
managed. So I think the possibility of
World War II is less right now and I'm
glad it is less. Will India achieve its
economic goals even even if there's
regime change? Well, it depends on what
kind of regime change there is. If there
is electoral regime change which means
next next election brings in a different
political party or coalition. Well,
that's an internal regime change, right?
is not a external regime change like
what happened in Bangladesh or Pakistan
which was essentially a coup done done
by the US. So if there is a democratic
regime change then the people's
aspirations will be met and yeah if if
the if there is a change of political
dispensation which means the BJP is not
in power in 2029 or wherever then there
will be a change of policies and maybe
the new government will take its take
you know bring the economy down it's
possible in which case India will not
achieve its economic goals but then the
people would have voted for not
achieving their economic goals I would
say
um So regime change has multiple
meanings. Regime change actually
essentially means that somebody else
from outside is doing a coup and
changing your regime from outside. If
that happens, God forbid, then India is
finished because whoever is strong
enough to to effect to execute a regime
change operation in India is going to be
not a well-wisher of India, right? In
which case India is doomed. So we don't
want that to happen and uh if it happens
India will not achieve any of its
economic
goals.
Um GGZ says how to set goals properly in
any digital app. Well it depends on what
app you use. I don't use any digital
apps for setting goals. I use pen and
paper. So I don't know. I'm sure there
are lots of digital the problem with
digital apps is that you know you don't
have ready access to it any given moment
in time. If you have paper then you can
take the paper anywhere and you can put
it out on demand in a digital map
digital app you have to take the device
if it's your cell phone or whatever uh
you know unlock the cell phone then find
the app open the app probably you've
logged into the app and then you to find
the thing it's a pretty there's a lot of
friction you know between what you want
to see and how long it takes to see it
and then
uh I don't know what are the what are
the popular apps Right now there are
calendar apps and list apps and to-do
list apps and the goal setting apps
and so I don't know it depends on the
architecture of the app and the
functionality and all that. Um yeah so
overall it how to set goals will depend
on the app itself. Every app will will
have its own way of setting goals.
Animeh Paul says, "As India rises
economically and strategically, how can
it navigate uh growing pressure from
major powers, protect its interests and
sustain progress without compromising
autonomy or long-term goals?" As we
rise, as we grow economically and
militarily, there's going to be more
pressure like you say Animesh from major
powers because nobody wants a new power
to rise.
The existing powers even though they may
be competing against each other even
though they may have they may have
adversarial relations with each other
they will agree that they don't want
more such powers to rise. So US, China,
Russia they'll say okay let let it be US
China and Russia we don't want a fourth
power to rise and so on. So there's
going to be pressure from the world to
uh to uh against India to keep India
down. So what does India do in this
situation? One thing we can do is that
we have to understand not everybody is
against us. There are lots of these
small nations, downtrodden nations that
actually would be very happy to see
India rise because we are we are a
civilization that has never exploited
others. We have never bullied others. So
we are not a threat to anybody. Right?
So all the African nations, all the
small nations here, there, everywhere,
they would love to see India rise. So we
need to take them along with us. We need
to have good relations with them. We
need to have a good outreach with them.
We need to have diplomacy ongoing on
daily basis with these nations. And we
need to invest in these nations wherever
possible. Do trade with them. If they
have resources that we need, we can help
them set up factories which will
generate employment and we will get the
resources and we will give them a fair
price for that. That sort of thing. So
we can all rise and grow together. That
sort of thing. That's one thing we can
do. The second thing is that our
economic growth needs to be non
negotiable there. There can be no
compromise about it. We have to keep on
growing economically at 6 7 8% whatever
is possible per year. And the right way
to do do that is through manufacturing.
The age of the services industry and the
IT industry may soon be a thing of the
past. We have to become a manufacturing
power. We have to replace China as the
world's manufacturing um uh center. And
uh to do that we will need some reforms
certain set of reforms the government
will have to do. So that's
non-negotiable. We have to keep on
growing economically. And with economic
growth will come military growth. And in
the military growth sphere we have to be
very very clear that we will we have to
make our arms procurement as indigenous
as possible. Atman Parat right see our
success in operation Sindu the three-day
war goes you know a lot of it can be
attributed to make in India the Akash
system is made in India and various
other other systems that we used were
made in India so you know the world has
now taken up stood up and taken notice
of our arms industry and we need to take
it further to the next level we need to
become indigenous and self-sufficient in
all arms procurement if we do these this
then we will be in a good position and
we will be able to sustain progress
without compromising autonomy or
long-term
goals. Ankita, thank you so much. Thank
you very
much. Bipla, thank you very
much. Dashan Patel says, "I took my
French exam recently, but I stumbled a
little. Can you give me some hope and
tips? I'm feeling down about how it
went. I'm at B1 level." Okay. I'm not
sure what a B1 level is. I've never
taken any levels in French. I know
French because I lived in a
French-speaking country for a certain uh
number of years as a kid. So, my French
is no longer as good as it used to be. I
you know, it's been a long time since I
had a proper conversation in French. So,
I I did not ever learn French formally.
I just absorbed it from everybody around
me. As you when you're a kid, you learn
very fast. Um so, what tips can I give
you? Look, if you want to learn a
language well, you have to immerse
yourself in the environment of the
language, which means that you have to
spend a certain amount of time every day
just thinking and speaking in that
language in the target language, French,
French. And you have to be very diligent
at it. U initially you have to absorb as
much vocabulary as possible, you know,
and the way to absorb vocabulary is not
to memorize words, but to use them in
whatever way you can. So that's how we
do it and ideally you should find
somebody else who can speak the language
and then you can converse with that
person a certain amount of time every
day and then every every exam will have
its own peculiarity so you to find out
what's the pattern of the exam and all
that. Uh my point is you know everything
is possible
uh with a certain with with with the
right amount of diligence and practice
and all I'm sure you will get much
better.
Uh beyond that I'm not sure what tips I
can give you because I don't know what a
B1 level means. Uh yeah but yeah
practice immerse yourself a certain
amount of time every day. The best way
to learn a language is by
immersion and uh yeah so all the best
sir all the
best. Narendra thank you very much. 27
returning to India want to start a
business for India's future. What would
you do in if you were in my place? I'm
eyeing eyeing solar plants. What are the
businesses of the future? How would you
contribute to the manufacturing sector?
H So you are 27 years old. You're
returning to India. Well, big step and
uh uh you want to start a business in
manufacturing. Well, first of all, I
would like to thank you for doing this
and I would like to wish you the best at
the at the very beginning. Now you're
eyeing solar plants. I think solar
plants is a
pretty reasonably
uh you could say it's is a reasonably
high-tech thing to do. India needs solar
power. India has a tremendous amount of
sunlight. So it makes sense to start a
business in solar plants. Makes makes a
lot of sense. What are the businesses of
of the future? Well, the businesses of
the future are businesses that have to
do with technology, with power
generation. So, it could be solar power.
It could be lithium. It could be in the
future sodium ion batteries, which could
be the next step after lithium after the
world moves on for from lithium. But
that's some that's something that is in
the research and development phase right
now. And if you want to have a
profitable business, you don't want to
go into R&D right now. I can obviously
it doesn't make sense. So, forget about
sodium ion batteries. So lithium and
lithium lithium ion batteries obviously
that that
is an industry of the future a business
of the future. Uh what else? Anything to
do with AI AI and automation and
robotics. Uh India needs uh you know
India's space program is is poised to
take off. So, anything that can be
connected to uh manufacturing components
for rockets or satellites, that could be
a thing, but I'm not sure it's it's
going to be there in in high demand
because only a few rocket launches per
year at this point. We're not launching
hundreds of rockets rockets per year. In
the future, it may happen, but we are
still not there yet. Uh drones and
military equipment is very much a
business of the future. India needs a
tremendous amount of military equipment.
you know whether it's missiles whether
it is parts of aircraft whether it is
parts for tanks or howitzers or guns or
arms or ammunition all of that is needed
that's always going to be an evergreen
business especially considering the kind
of neighborhood India has uh drones
obviously uh whether it is surveillance
drones whether it is kabikazi drones so
anything to do with defense is going to
be an evergreen industry it's going to
be and because of the technological race
you going to need more and more
high-tech
um systems in place. So that's a
business of the future. Then anything
that can solve the problems of people
um and and automate things and all that.
So AI and robotics. So these are some of
the businesses I I can think of and I
think solar plants is a great it's a
great place to start off with. So it
makes sense to to invest in solar
plants. In the future, you'll also have
nuclear energy, but obviously that's a
very niche thing, you know, modular
nuclear reactors and stuff. So, I think
solar plants is is a great business.
It's a great industry to get into. So,
Narendra, all the best. I really
appreciate what you're doing and I wish
you nothing but
success. Hardik Jooshi says, "How do you
think marriage as a concept in India
will change given the rise in prosperity
and economic westernization in India? Is
there a correlation?" I think India is
showing signs of of going down the road
the west has gone down. You know today I
mean historically people would get
married and they would not have any
girlfriends and boyfriends and 20
different affairs and 50 different
partners and stuff. But that's
increasingly the norm these days it
looks like especially in urban centers
you know live in relationships and it
fails and you move on to somebody else
that sort of thing. Um traditionally we
were never like that. We were never a
promiscuous society and today it's it's
becoming the norm. So we have we are
absorbing uh this this kind of uh
lifestyle from the west. Um it's nothing
to do with the rise of prosperity. India
was super prosperous in the past. India
accounted for at least a third of the
world's GDP for the longest part of
history and we were never a promiscuous
society back then. So a rise in
prosperity is not necessarily something
that will uh end marriage. It is the
absorb absorption of western culture
into Indian society that will possibly
uh create problems in the institution of
marriage.
Um yeah so right now I think that
especially in urban places urban centers
the there's a rise rise in divorce
cases rise in breakdown of marriages
rise in promiscuity all of that all of
this there's a correlation with the
westernization of India not economic
westernization of India but sociological
societal cultural westernization of
India we are becoming dassinated our
education system doesn't teach us about
our culture our our most people you know
every single generation that passes
becomes more and more devassinated. So
in most families increasingly it's the
case in many families especially in
urban cities urban centers that parents
aren't connected to their culture and
that's why children are even more
alienated from their culture and that's
why the only culture that's available is
the western culture because it's all
over the media and so on so forth. So
you become like that. So that's a it's a
growing trend in India and that could
destroy the institution of marriage and
then you can have I I suppose like in
the US you know most mothers will be
single mothers and that's a disaster for
any society. So I hope we don't go down
that road but it looks like we
are. St. Crocodile says how did Vic
culture start? We have no idea. Um you
know we have portions of of the rigida
the riged is the oldest literature known
to humankind
and the earliest Vic culture is said
said to be the the culture from our our
ancestral culture from the time of the
rigeda it was a very different India
back then back then a very different bat
it was not an urban civilization it was
a rural pastoral civilization and the
population density of the subcontinent
would have been much lower than what it
is today we don't know We don't quite
know when the Rig Veeda was written.
Some people say it's 1500 BC. Those who
believe in the Arian invasion myth, I
would say it's closer to 6,000 BC, maybe
even before that. Uh, and before that
there would have been a pre- Vdic
culture, the protodic culture, and that
would go back more than 10,000 years
possibly. We don't quite have a good
idea of the dates. The dates that are
put forth by various uh researchers vary
wildly. Some people say it's 30,000 BC.
Some people say it's 1500 BC and so on.
So huge variance is there. So we don't
quite know how did it start. Well, how
it started is because about 70,000 years
ago there was a migration out of Africa
and people settled in India and they
formed what would eventually become the
Vic culture. Those are our
ancestors. Ankita, thank you very much
once again. Thank you. Geopolitical
Dubet. Thank you very much. Thank you
for your contribution.
Uh Stark Vincent says, "I live and work
in the US. My co-workers and my manager
are from Pakistan. Ever since the war,
it's been hard to manage the
relationships. Any advice?" I It's very
simple. Be professional. Just be
professional. You don't need to have a
personal rel relationship with these
individuals.
And if the if the situation isn't good
and if if it becomes hard for you to
keep working in that job, find a
different job. That's what I would say.
Uh of often times it's the case that you
know you spend the most part of your
life at at work. So those people who are
your co-workers, they become your
friends and social circle. That's often
the case. You know, it may not be
supposed to be like that, but it often
becomes the case. Um and if all your
co-workers are Pakistanis, Pakistani
origin people, your managers Pakistani
origin, then it could certainly be a pro
problem. So advice number one, as far as
possible, just keep it purely
professional. Keep all personal things
out of the relationship. And if it is
not a viable long-term option, switch
jobs. That that's what I can say. Yeah,
it's it's a problem when you have when
you are surrounded by people from
Pakistan, people of Pakistani origin. So
I have in the past worked in the US. I
have I had
Pakistanis. I don't remember a single
Pakistani but I I knew a lot of
Pakistani taxi drivers. Uh so it depends
on which industry you're in. I'm not
saying you are from that that industry.
Uh but yeah so all I would say is try
and keep it
professional and if it doesn't work
maybe you should find a different
job. Okay. All the best. All the best.
Rajput Marata says, "Tell me about
possible Rajput origin of Kandesh
people." Uh, it's something that I have
not looked into. So I would not be able
to tell you about the possible Rajput
origin of that. Very sorry. Very sorry.
Jendra
it kicker says one of the biggest
internal weaknesses that could prevent
India from becoming a major global power
by
2047. Greetings from Dehadun. Greetings
sir. The major internal
weaknesses. Well the first major
internal weakness is
corruption. I think every Indian the
moment I say this will understand what I
mean. Corruption. That's the biggest one
of the top three possibly number one
internal weakness. Second is lack of
merit in
society reservations all over the place
in government jobs hopefully not beyond
that that's another problem right the
third thing is that you know the Indian
bureaucracy is not being reformed and a
bureaucrat once you become a bureaucrat
you have a job for life which means that
you can never be sacked any Indian
government officer when they caught for
corruption whenever it happens you will
see they are
suspended they are not terminated
suspended means you are put on
administrative leave for a number of
days or weeks or months and then you
come back to the job. So these are big
problems within India and then you have
this the other biggest internal weakness
is the 100 million plus possible uh
foreign infiltrators who live in India.
So this is just a small sampling of the
big weaknesses we have and without
unless we we we address these problems
we will not rise to the fullest extent
of our potential we may remain a
mediocre uh you know not a great power
so we have to address these
problems desai thank you so much for
your contribution sir appreciate
it inferno says do you see any
similarities between Modi's first Trump
term and Trump's second term from the
point of view of foreign travel context
India's image then US debt now I see
absolutely no similarities whatsoever
and you don't measure the quality or
impact of a prime ministerial term or
presidential
term based on one metric which is how
much foreign travel happened what was
the total amount of hours sent by spent
by the leader traveling abroad that's
not the metric you measure you you look
at it the the the term from a different
set of metrics you uh economic growth
and uh the kind of uh political
uh international relations you have and
the amount of investment that comes to
into your country and whether you're
achieving your geopolitical geostrategic
objectives or not and so on so forth. Um
Modi's first term, Trump's second term
um Trump's second term has just started
and he has done only one major foreign
trip thus far which was to the Middle
East. So I I I really really don't see
how we can compare the two right India's
image then US debt now once again I
don't how do you compare image with debt
not sure how you
compare Prabhav says do you think AI
will eat most of the jobs what will the
humans do then is AI will not will only
be smarter as the time passes well it's
a it's a huge huge problem coming up AI
will eat many of the jobs most jobs are
you
See most jobs in especially a nation
like India and third world countries are
unskilled labor just repetitive jobs
assembly line line manufacturing and
sweeping the floor on the streets or
whatever very very repetitive low low
skill jobs will eat all of those jobs
for breakfast everything will be
automated at a much lower price than
what it costs to hire human employees so
it will make no business sense to burn
money on human employees when AI will do
the same thing at a much higher standard
quality standard at a much lower cost.
So all those jobs will be wiped out by
AI. What can humans do then? You have to
ski upskill. You have to acquire skills
that can't be replaced by AI. So people
are saying in the future content
creation will become uh you know will
will will disappear because of AI. I
completely disagree. Content creation is
the one I'm just giving one example.
Okay, content creation, what I am doing
here right now, it's a very human thing.
It's the one thing AI can't replace.
See, today if you'll see AI generated
videos, most people hate those videos.
Even though they are very pretty, very
high quality, etc., you can somehow tell
it's it's it's synthetic, it's
artificial, and it'll never have that
human quality, human human emotion. So,
I think one example of a job AI can't
replace is content creation. Um, and
there'll be some other jobs also. So you
have to become AI native. You have to
you have to uh be able to manage AI. I
think most jobs in the future will hinge
around managing AI systems. So it's
essentially like you have AI employees
and you manage the employees. You
delegate tasks to them. You monitor and
supervise what they're doing. You give
feedback and you train them and so on so
forth. That's what's going to be the
future of jobs. managing AI systems,
managing AI agents, managing AI uh
employees. So most jobs are going to be
like that. And then you're going to have
the entry of robotics, AI enabled
robotics in in industry. So today you
have all this low low skill labor that
is you know let's say you have you have
an Amazon warehouse or a blinket
warehouse. So when the when an order
comes in, you're given the order the
details and you are you're supposed to,
you know, take those products and and
and uh pack them in containers in
packages in parcels and then stack the
shelves and things like that. All of
that in the future will be done at a
much higher level of competence and
quality by AI enabled robotic workers.
So you're going to have dark warehouses
where you have robots that that can see
in the dark because of infrared or
whatever.
uh not infrared maybe ultraviolet
whatever you know they they can see in
the dark and they will do the the work
without the need for human intervention
with 0% error rates. So once again the
only job that is left then is to manage
the AI and robotic workers. So what
needs what humans need to do is they
have to upskill themselves. They have to
become AI native and they have to learn
how to interact with AI and how to
manage AI.
And some jobs obviously will never go
away. As of now, construction jobs uh
right now we don't have construction
robots, right? We don't have robots that
build bridges and build railway
networks, railway tracks and uh lay down
roads and so on. So those jobs will
remain but eventually down the line even
those could be replaced by by robotics.
So we'll have to see. So the main thing
is we have to keep on evolving and
adapting and
learning. Nandanda Kishor Ra says, "Is
it safe to live 30 ft from a phone
tower? If not, what's the safe distance
especially for elders? Please guide me.
Wanted to buy a plot." I've never looked
into this. I don't know.
Um it is said that you know the higher
the frequency the the more dangerous it
can be for living beings. Uh so I would
say you know just to be safe live at
least 100 100 ft from a phone tower.
Yeah. I've not really looked into the
the matter myself. I mean I I mean we
all have you know radio signals, phone
signals right next to us because of the
devices we carry. But phone towers they
are they have much higher output in
terms of wattage the power output. So
I'm not sure what effect it has on
humans. I've never really done the
calculations and looked into it but I
would say just to be safe keep at least
100 ft distance just to be safe.
Hardik Jooshi says, "Excuse me, as a
physicist, how accurate or true is Vic
astrology?" Look, I have no idea. I have
never studied Vic astrology. I've not
studied any form of astrology. Um, so I
cannot tell you how accurate or true it
is because I have zero knowledge or
competence in this matter.
Sorry. Susant, first of all, thank you
very much. Namaste. I came across your
Chingish Khan video four years ago and
I've been learning from you ever since.
I'm a much more confident and wiser
version of myself. Thank you for
everything. Thank you very much sir. I
really appreciate it and thank you for
your contribution. Thank
you. Vision of Hindu Rashtra. Thank you
very much. Thank you very much sir.
Jadev Tucker says um truly inspired by
your fearless clarity. Thank you. I've
been trying to invite you to our hotel 7
sky in
Bhkatch. It would be a blessing if you
could visit someday. Tried many ways to
reach out. How to reach? Uh look at the
uh description portion of this video.
The description in that my email id is
there. So if you want to email me, you
can email me there. I would I would love
to come to BJ and thank you so much for
the for the
invitation. Uh I think it's an honor and
a privilege. I would love to come and
meet you in BJ. Never been to BJ. I I
hear it's a beautiful part of our
country. I would love to visit. So,
please email me. My email id is there in
the description of this video. Just find
it and email me and I'll I'll I'd love
to uh you know uh come there. It it
it'll be an honor for me. Thank you so
much. Appreciate it.
Aris Manticor says China is developing
its sixth generation fighter jets
variants with AI. Of course, they'll do
it. They'll do it and so should we. So
the point is we should not be left
behind. If the Chinese are doing it,
others are also doing it. We should not
be left behind. Ideally, we should be at
the forefront of this field. But at
least we can catch up. So yes, India
should take cognizance of this matter
and India should make sure that we also
take the necessary steps. Aris Mantor
says should we leverage India's
consumers and start investing in
absolute recycling technology if we push
enough should be we should we should be
close to selfsufficiency.
uh absolute recycling
technology I think we should start with
basic recycling technology for for
example if you go to any metropolitan
area today that's a big population in
even medium-sized towns in India have
large populations so each population
center is going to produce waste garbage
junk right
trash and sometimes in in some of these
cities and towns they're going to ask
you to segregate the waste wet waste,
dry waste, plastic waste, this waste,
that waste. So you segregate everything
as as a citizen and then the
municipality will take it away and then
what you find is that they will dump
everything in the same place again. They
just they just making a putting on a
show. One hears such stories sometimes.
Okay, I'm not saying it's happening
everywhere. I'm sure there are places
where it's done properly, but many
municipalities over here are not doing
enough or rather not doing anything
possibly when it comes to recycling.
Just take all the trash and dump it in
in a landfill and just let the landfill
grow in size and become a mountain and
there's no recycling done. In many
places, one hears that the sewage is
dumped into into rivers. Untreated
sewage goes into rivers or perhaps in
into the ocean sometimes, you know,
depending on where you are. I'm not
saying everywhere it's the case. I'm
sure there are places where it's done
properly. My point is let's start with
basic recycling. Let's treat all the
sewage with before it's thrown into into
any water body. For example, whether
it's running water or stagnant water,
let's treat all sewage. Let's uh recycle
as much as possible all the
trash. And once we can start doing that
properly every in every part of the
country then we can you know maybe
invest in better recycling technology.
Um and absolutely absolute recycling
means you are recycling absolutely
everything. So nothing goes to waste and
everything is repurposed. So if you have
metal all the metal is extracted and
reused and and so on so forth and a lot
of the the electronic waste today has
you know rare earths and whatnot. So
that can be recycled if we can find a
way to extract it. So if we do that then
we could be close to self-sufficiency
for sure. We could be significantly
closer to our end goal of
self-sufficiency.
Vina Jooshi says, "Podcast on brainwash
Republic with Niraj Atri G." Okay. Um, I
haven't done that but I'd be very happy
to consider it in the future.
Yes. Uh, Prashant P says, "Okay, thank
you very much." Thank you very much,
sir. I appreciate that. Aayush says,
"What happened to Russia, the recent
deal with Pakistan?" I hear some rumors
of Russia doing some um some kind of
manufacturing deal with Pakistan, steel
or something. I'm not sure how true it
is. Um, sometimes the media likes to
create stories. So, I've heard of this.
I have not seen any indication that this
is actually a true thing. In case it's
true, then maybe we need to take this up
with Russia. But thus far, I'm not sure
if it is
true. Okay, let's do a very quick Google
search and see if if there is any new
information on this. Russia deal with
Pakistan.
Russia deal with Pakistan. Let's see.
Putin shocks Russ shocks India. Tensions
with India. Pakistan makes Russia
dismisses Pakistan media reports. See,
looks like this this news came from
Pakistani
media. So news on air is it? Oh, it's an
okay. This is a government website which
explains the quality.
Russia dismisses Pakistani media reports
of Moscow's plan to expand economic ties
with Islamabad. Um these media reports
Russia says are fake which claim that
Moscow is expanding diplom economic ties
with Islamabad including plans to
jointly set up steel meals in Karachi.
The reports stemmed from a May 13
meeting between Harun Aktar Khan special
assistant to Pakistan's prime minister
and Russian envoy Dennis Nazir. Moscow
firmly denied any stated multi-billion
dollar deal accusing elements of
Pakistan of trying to disrupt the strong
IndiaRussia strategic partnership
especially after India's recent
operation Zindur targeting terror camps
in Pakistan and PK. A senior Russian
official called the reports exaggerated
and said they aim to sensationalize time
ties that do not exist at such a scale.
So from this news report on EIR it looks
like it is a fiction. So I think what we
should do is we should wait and watch
and see how the story evolves. If it is
true then the truth will come out right
but often these these these stories are
planted just to to create friction
between two
countries. Yetan Kumar says how long can
the US stay strong while debt is rising?
The US will stay strong while debt is
rising as long as it has the world's
most powerful military and they have the
kind of power projection ability they
have today. See the world accepts the US
dollar as the default currency because
of US military power projections which
is something most people can't see but
it's something that nations are
accurately aware of. So the US has power
projection abilities all across the
world. They have more than 700 extr
territorial military bases and that is
how they enforce the rule of the US or
the role of the US dollar as the world's
reserve currency as long as that is
enforced the debt doesn't matter because
the debt will have to be repaid in US
dollars only right so they can just
print dollars and repay the debt it'll
obviously mess up the the global market
and create um inflation everywhere but
yeah if it comes to that they can do it
so as long as their military might
dominates they'll be able to say stay
strong Patel says why are the
left-wingers especially the Indian
left-wing academicians so keen on
proving that Arians did not originate in
India interesting question I was
discussing this with somebody today
arian invasion it's been a long time
since I've really paid a lot of
attention to that in 2016 or 17 I was
one of the first people to write a
comprehensive article
debunking the RN inversion myth. Um, now
the question, okay, let let's find that
my article and I'll I'll I'll give you
I'll read out an excerpt from that which
answers your question. So, here it is.
Uh, okay.
Aran in invasion myth Abijit
Chavan. Okay, one second. Let me get my
own spelling right. Here we are. The
Arian invasion myth. Uh, where shall we
take? Okay. So, let's go to medium. I
think this is my old medium article.
Please get rid of this. So, this is is
an article from May 2017. So, let me go
to the it's a very long article. It
gives you a comprehensive overview of
why this entire theory Arian
invasion/migration it's a complete myth.
It's a complete lie. I've given you
multi-disciplinary multi-dimensional
evidence of that in this article.
And
now, okay, here is is
is the the section that I'm going to
read out to you. So, I've given all this
evidence in 2017 and since then there is
more more evidence that's come to light.
So, will the new evidence set the
controversy to rest? So, here's my
answer. The question of the origin of
the Indo-Aryans concerns the very idea
of India. The mainstream Arian invasion
or migration narrative which portrays
Indo-Aryan or Hindu culture as
hegemonic, racist, intolerant, rapious
and in egalitarian imposes an Indian
version of white guilt of on people of
Indo-arian ancestry and engenders deep
resentment and a desire to write
historical wrongs amongst people of
so-called Dravidian and so-called Dalid
ancestry which manifests itself in
various forms such as separatism and
rejection of Hinduism. M and Indian
culture among others and I could have
you know essentially this this Dravidian
race thing is also a complete fiction
and a complete fabrication of this
theory. There is no Arian or Dravidian
race. We are all Indians. So this makes
the iron invasion theory a powerful
political tool which dovetales perfectly
with the leftist secular and liberal
political narrative as well as with the
agendas of Dravidian nationalists,
Dalith, suprematist, supremacists,
missionaries, separatists and other
breaking India forces internal as well
as external. As such, it has long been
used to to neatly divide India into
dichomous categories such as North and
South Indians, Arians and Ravidians,
fair-skinned and dark-kinned people,
so-called high high cast and so-called
Dalits, the privileged and the
oppressed. It is difficult to overstate
how much the Arian invasion theory has
strengthened the leftist narrative and
so on and so forth. The left secular
liberal ecosystem derives much of its
strength and power from its decades old
strangle old on Indian academia
especially in the humanities and so on
um and so on so
forth. Um these people they monopolize
academic discourse and marginalize
dissenting voices. The leftist clique
has ensured that every school college
and university textbook teaches the
Arian invasion theory. This theory gives
the gives the leftist academics the
ideal rational for denigrating Indian
culture. Exhorting so-called lowclass
students to reject Hinduism and rebel
against the establishment. Encouraging
female students to reject Hinduism for
being patriarchal and misogynistic.
Calling into question India's right to
res exist as a nation and supporting
anti-inational and separatist movements
all on academic and scholarly grounds.
This is the modus operandi by which
several generations of unquestioning and
impressionable students have been
indoctrinated and recruited into the
leftist movement. So the iron invasion
theory is thus the academic premise
underpinning the entire spectrum of
methods that the various breaking India
forces employ to attack India's culture
and inter under undermine India's
integrity. It is their trump card. Take
it away and they have nothing else left.
It is therefore vitally important that
for them that this theory remains the
dominant narrative in India and so on.
You can read the article. So as you can
see that's why these people are so keen
on proving that Arians did not originate
in India. It's a complete lie but it is
the trump
card. Rahul thank you so much. Thank you
very much sir. Aries Manticor says, "Do
we need to be a more strict,
disciplined, and more ruthless society
like that of China? The world not only
belittles them but fears them as well.
We need to raise our standards." What is
the meaning of raising your standards?
Being more
disciplined, being being stricter with
standards, being more ruthless, don't
don't waste your time or nonsense. Focus
and and and go after what you
want. We need to be that. How do you
think our society was during the reign
of Chandra Gupta Moria or Ashok Moria?
Do you think people were the way they
are today? No, there was way more
discipline. How do you think we were
under the under the rule of Emperor
Kadeshka? Do you think we were the way
we are today? It was a more disciplined
society under the under the rule of
Kumar Gupta or Chandra Gupta the first
or Scand Gupta or Samud Gupta. Do you
think India was a nation of Jugar and
and and Joltah? India was not that way.
So we have to evolve into a much more
disciplined society, a more focused
society, a society of much higher
standards. Only then will we achieve our
objectives to hell with what the world
thinks and cares. I don't care what the
world thinks of us. We have objective of
objectives of our own and we must
achieve those objectives. Let the world
say whatever it wants. It doesn't
matter. So for that we have to become
more disciplined. We have to become a
more organized, more ruthless, more
stricter society, stricter with our
standards and so
on. K dot impersonator says opinion
opinions on Imran Khan's politics and
jail time. Okay. Immran Khan was a great
leader in the in the field of sports,
one of the greatest sports people the
Pakistan produced, one of the greatest
all-rounders and so on. great fast
bowler, great batsman, great captain and
he had the leadership qualities and uh
after he retired he became a politician
and I remember seeing a an interview of
him on BBC about 15 years ago in which
he was saying that we will we don't want
western money is poison money because
you've used this money to to to control
us and and to to you know do whatever
you've done with us that sort of thing
it's poison money we don't need your
money. We need to be independent from
the west. That sort of thing he he used
to say back then. Then when he got the
opportunity to become the prime
minister, he kissed the ring of the
military and became a military puppet.
As prime minister, he tried to bring his
country closer to China than to the
US. And the US then did a regime change
operation in the year 2022 which toppled
Imran Khan, brought a new puppet to
power and ever since then Imran Khan has
been in prison. That's the long and the
short of it.
U I I clearly you can admire his his
cricket. He was a great cricketer as a
politician. He had
good what what did he have? He he had
good intentions I suppose for his
country not for us. He he would have
never been a good friend of India. Uh
but he had good intentions for his
country I suppose but didn't work out
for him. So turns out he is no different
from others. He could not achieve what
he wanted to achieve. So see the only
yard stick the only yard stick by which
you can measure a leader is whether they
succeed or fail. Opinions I mean you
know
uh their objectives their intentions
don't matter. Oh he had good intentions.
I don't care. The only yard stick by
which you measure a leader a leader's uh
performance
is the output is is what they're able to
achieve or not whether they succeed or
fail. Okay. Akar says if we develop
advanced engines for our missiles like
Agni the uh HSTDV etc hypersonic
technology demonstrated vehicle etc.
Then why is it so difficult? What is so
difficult about developing the cavari
engine? Very different set of
technologies. So we have outstanding
missile engines, agni, the hypersonic
engine, u supersonic scramjet engines,
uh ramjet uh in in the case of the
bramos and so on. The cavary engine is a
different beast. See a rocket engine or
a missile engine is the same thing and
it's a much more simpler system than a
turboan engine which is the cavity
engine. So in a turopan engine you have
uh you know these these blades the the
the blades that are part of the turboan.
These blades have to be made of some
kind of substance that can withstand
incredibly high pressures and
temperatures.
So, the temperatures could be in excess
of of 1,500, maybe in excess of 2,000° C
at
times. And you your turbine blades need
to be able to withstand those
temperatures and perform well in those
temperatures. And they need to be able
to withstand these temperatures for
hours at a
time, right? So, ideally, you want an
engine to be overhauled only once a 100
hours or something. After 100 hours of
flight time, you can initially have a
lower standard, maybe 20 hours, 30
hours, 40 hours. Eventually, it should
be 100 hours.
So, when it comes to temperatures like
2,000°
C, most metals melt at these
temperatures, right? So, how do you
manufacture turbine blades that can
withstand temperatures that most metals
will melt at? All metals will melt.
Let's quickly see what's the melting
point of steel and so on and so forth. H
for example mel melting point of
steel what's the melting
point 1300 to 1500° right but uh in in
the case of a jet engine you will have
higher temperatures and melting point of
iron I mean you don't know use iron in
jet engines and so on. So the point is
even if you use
alloys they will only work well if they
are made from a single metallic crystal
and those single metallic crystals also
need to have you know
uh certain holes in them so that you
know gas can pass and cool the thing. So
it's a very complicated thing and the
western countries have been able to
develop this technology over decades of
experimentation and we are we have had a
stop start program in the cavary engine
some governments will fund it for a few
years then stop it for a few years then
start again for a few years then again
stop it that's not how we develop a jet
engine so that's why it is so
difficult but right now I think we have
a reasonably good covery engine with I
don't know how many kilograms of
kilonton of thrust maybe around 50 to 70
konton of dry thrust I think we can
start using that in some
aircraft as long as it's reliable I'm
sure it is and then slowly iteratively
make it a more powerful version of the
engine it takes time it takes decades
takes generations for this to happen so
what India needs to do is purchase jet
engine technology at whatever price from
whoever maybe France maybe Russia maybe
whoever and at the same time keep on
developing the cavary engine in paralle
That's what needs to
happen. Okay. Akar says, "Why don't
doesn't ISRO or Indian space startups
develop super heavy lift rockets? If
money is scars, why don't our
billionaires fund such
startups?" I don't know why. See, ISRO
the the engineers and scientists at
ISRO, I'm sure they would love to
develop a
heavy heavy lift lift
rocket, but the money has to come from
the government, right? The go ahead has
to be given, the approval has to be
given from the government of India. The
government of India doesn't seem to see
this as a to regard this as a big
priority for India. So we still have the
little PSLV. We are very proud of the
PSLV. It's a great rocket. It's a little
rocket in the grand scheme of things.
The GSLV or whatever it's called these
days, you know, it's got a new name
these days, LM large, whatever it's
called. It's also a medium at best a
medium lift
rocket. Even now we we are forced to
have sometimes the Arian rocket lift
certain satellites to space because our
GSLV or whatever it's called now can't
lift it. We're still in that in that
situation where we sometimes have to
depend on foreign uh launch providers.
Sometimes even SpaceX is lifting is
taking Indian rockets Indian uh
spacecraft or satellites into into
orbit. So I just don't know why we are
not doing this. Why isn't the government
um giving ISRO the direction the the
order to develop more powerful
rockets? I hear that some programs are
are under underway which will take
another 10 20 years to to come to
fruition maybe 5 years 10 years. Why
don't we have a he heavy lift rocket by
today? I just don't get it. Why aren't
we developing reusable rocket boosters?
Rocket boosters that can land
themselves. Why SpaceX did that I don't
know how many 20 years ago? We what are
we doing? I just don't get it. We seem
to have zero ambition when it comes to
space. And if we get left behind in
space, then we will be relegated by the
end of the century to to a backwater of
the world. Um billionaires look
billionaires will look at their own
business and industry, right? They will
look at their own bank balance. they
will invest in something only if it
makes economic sense from the
perspective of an investor. So that's
why it's the government that needs to
take take these things up especially in
these in certain sectors where where
investors will come in only at a later
stage. Initially the government has to
take the risk of of investing in these
things because it's it's it's it's a
national security imperative right so
yeah Sergeant Skyland says middle income
trap okay which question was that
uh
okay yeah it was something to do with
India's GDP okay got it got it thank
you Bhavik Vader says I am 23 years old
working in Canada currently as a
supertore manager. I make good money but
I feel trapped at this job. Please
advise. Look my friend Bik first of all
you're 23 years
old.
Okay people lot of people would give
anything to be 23 years old. You're just
starting off in life. You have a long
long long way ahead of you. You're just
starting. First of all you need to
realize that. Secondly, I am so happy to
hear that you're making good
money now. You're feeling trapped in the
job. You need advice. Here's my advice.
You're just starting off. First of all,
take that into cognizance. Number two,
the good money that you're making, save
as much of it as
possible. As much of it as
possible. Ideally, more than 50% of it.
Just save it. You can invest it if
possible, but no high-risisk
investments. Do this for I don't know
two three years if possible until you're
26. Do it for two or three years until
you have a good stash of
money. Then you can move out of the job
and maybe invest in something. Maybe
start your own business. If you have
entrepreneurial aspirations or
tendencies and the and the skills for
that and if you have that then you
should learn how to how to be an
entrepreneur which means you need to
take some business uh classes or
something. So that's what you should do.
You're very young. You're unhappy in the
job but the job is making good money. So
just slog for a while 2 three years save
the money. Save as as much as possible.
Then that asset that you will gain at
the end of two three years, you can
deploy it somewhere else to serve. You
see what buys you freedom is money.
Money doesn't buy you happiness
necessarily, but without money there's
no happiness. Money buys you freedom. So
once you have a decent stash of money at
your disposal, then you'll be free to do
whatever you want with with your with
your time, with your life. So I would
say don't don't be discouraged. There
are lots of people who have slogged for
decades and decades before making decent
money. So just save the money and then
you can decide how to redeploy it at a
given at at a at a more suitable
time. So they say first of all thank you
very much sir. Uh I am currently in
hospitality for uh for currently working
in the hotels industry for a year in the
US. I wish to go to Japan and work there
for a few years but my ultimate ambition
is to become a diplomat. How can I
achieve that? Well, if you want to
become a diplomat, uh first of all, I'm
not sure what country you're a citizen
of. If you are a citizen of India, then
the only way to become a diplomat is to
do the UPSC thing. Go the UPSC route. Uh
which means that you have to pass the
UPSC exam in India. And if you achieve a
certain score, you can go into the
Indian foreign services and then you
have a certain training period in the
government of India, Ministry of
External Affairs. And that's that's how
you eventually become a diplomat.
Uh I'm not sure if there is lateral
entry right now in the Indian foreign
services. U if there's going to be
lateral entry in the future in the
Indian foreign services, it will not be
in the position of a diplomat but maybe
in an advisory or consultative role in
the future. Uh so the way to become a
diplomat in India, an Indian diplomat is
to give the UPSC
exam, pass it, crack it and then get
into the Ministry of External Affairs.
That's the only way to do it. If you are
Indian, uh if you
are American, then they have their own
procedure. They have a lot they have
much they have the world's largest
diplomatic
uh uh core in the world. So if you're an
American citizen, well then it's much
easier to become a diplomat if you have
as long as you have certain skills. The
skills could be linguistic skills. If
you can speak a good Japanese then you
can become a diplomat in Japan and so
on. Um so yeah it depends which
citizenship you have. If it's an Indian
citizenship and you want to be become a
diplomat then you have to come back to
India study for the UPSC exam and then
crack it and then get it's a very very
uh high risk thing and there's a very
low probability of success but if you
are really good at it and if you are
super determined you can do it. Um yeah
so that's the only way you can do it if
you are an Indian citizen but if it's
not at the top of your list of
priorities then yeah go to Japan work
there wonderful place one of my favorite
countries in the world and uh yeah you
can make a career in the hospitality
industry possibly if that is another
option that you see for yourself. So
anyway, all the
best. Draj Kamat says, "A few years
back, a few hours back, sorry, I saw a
video from some Indian news outlet
claiming that India did lose a few
aircraft against Pakistan. Are these
channels deliberately trying to have us
lose the narrative war?" The problem is
not these Indian channels. The problem
is the Indian chief of defense
staff who went and spoke to gave an
interview to I think Bloomberg an
American channel in which I'm not sure
what exactly he said but it is being
interpreted by most Indian and
international observers as an admission
that India may have lost at least one
aircraft in the three-day war. I don't
understand why the chief of defense
staff has to go and give an interview to
a foreign channel. How does it serve
India's national
interest and if he does give an
interview to foreign channel why make
statements claiming this or that or
whatever that we even if we lost let's
say an aircraft or two or whatever why
make the admission in case he has made
the admission I'm not sure what is going
on and why this is happening and then
everybody will obviously take advantage
of this look to put it in
perspective losing an aircraft or two in
a war is no big deal the American ans
are engaged in a military operation
against the Houthi rebels in Yemen. The
Houthis are a rebel force according to
the west itself and while being engaged
in military operations against a group
of rebels, the Americans lost two F-18
fighter planes. Now is the world trying
to say that the Americans have lost the
war to the Houthis? Nobody's trying to
say it. But when it comes to India
Pakistan, they are trying to claim first
of all that India lost whatever number
of fighter planes allegedly and then it
and secondly that it means that India
has somehow lost the war. Both are
nonsensical
claims. Um so what can I say? My my main
thing is why does the Indian chief of
defense staff have to give an interview
to Bloomberg and American channel and
then makes make whatever statements he
made. I just don't understand it. It is
incomprehensible to me. I just don't
understand what what's going on. What
are you trying to achieve? I don't I
don't get it. So, more than these TV
channels, I
would ask myself, what is our chief of
defense staff trying to do? What is he
trying to achieve? Big questions over
here. I I'm I'm
I'm flabbergasted. I don't have any
answers at this point. Don't get
it. Huh? Wenet god. Uh, thank you very
much. Thank you very much sir. Karthikb
says there are no more Nazis today
because the Nazi ideology has been
exposed and put to rest. Do you see a
similar thing happening with Islamic
terror or would geopolitical forces are
they going to use it forever and what's
the role of India? Um look Nazi ideology
there are Nazis even today. First of all
uh there is this neo-Nazi movement in
various parts of Europe. I'm not sure if
it's a very well-known thing, but there
is a neo-Nazi movement in Germany.
There's a neo-Nazi movement in Ukraine
very much so. There are many Nazis in
Ukraine. Zalinski brought a Nazi, a
former Nazi armed forces, person who
served in the armed forces to the
Parliament of Canada and the Canadian
MPs all stood up and applauded this
Nazi. So, there still are Nazis today.
Many of these Nazis are not in jail.
Many of them are young. many of them
want to revive the Nazi movement. A lot
of the Ukrainian population is still
Nazified and so on. So, you
know, it's impossible to
completely end any ideology as long as
it has favor among the people. Now, when
it comes to what you're talking about,
well, Islam is the is either the first
or the second most popular religion in
the world, right? Let let's find out
what's the number of practicing Muslims
in the world. Let's go to Google and
find out. Largest religions in the
world,
right?
Largest
religions in the what happened?
Religions. The largest religion is
Christianity. It's followed by Islam and
Hinduism. So, Christianity has 2.6
billion followers and Islam has 2.0
billion followers. Hinduism is 1.2.
Buddhism is half a billion and so
on. So look, if if certain people would
like to engage in the practice of
terrorism while ascribing it to a
certain religion which happens to be the
second largest religion in the world, um
there's nothing the world can do about
it. Right? So yeah, I don't see u such
tendencies of using any religion as the
basis of doing terrorism. I don't think
I don't see such tend tendencies ever
dying out and when such tendencies
tendencies exist geopolitical forces
will certainly want to use them. So it
is what it
is and it's not going
anywhere. Jussi says namaste. Which
airline do you like? Air India. I would
love to love Air India. I would love to
but Air India standards need a lot of
improvement for sure. Right. Uh the
airline I I use the most when I travel
within India is most likely most likely
Indigo. Um I've I've used Air India also
quite often and internationally
whichever whichever is available I will
take it. I would I would love to use Air
India for everything but they really
need to do something about their
standards the quality. I know it's a
long process and it's not the fault of
whoever is in charge right now but it
needs to we need to see a visible
improvement and I hope that happens. I
would love to see our airline national
airline as being one of the best in the
world. You
know Kajuro Bthornne says out of the
five sovereign nations India is the only
one that is not a surveillance state. Is
this a disadvantage? Thoughts on the
East German stashi.
Um so out of the four out of the five
sovereign nations one is the US absolute
police state no question about it
surveillance state 24 by7. Second is
China absolute police state absolute
surve absolute surveillance state
Russia it also is kind of not to the
it's not a police state to the extent of
Russia of the US or China but yes you
have a significant police presence and
there is surveillance for sure Israel
very militarized society lot of
surveillance India the absolute opposite
of all these nations right we are the
only sovereign nation out of the five
which is not a police state where the
police are not in charge of of of you
know controlling the population because
the population is not some a population
that needs to be controlled or needs to
be bullied and we don't have the kind of
surveillance that we have in all the
other uh nations that we're talking
about. Is this a
disadvantage? I think it's actually a
good
thing as you know we have a big problem
in India which is the illegal
infiltrators maybe 100 million of them.
Once we get rid of them, we really don't
need to be a surveillance state or a
police state. So I think it's it's a
great strength of our society that we
function very well as a so society
despite not being a police state or a or
a or a surveillance state. I think it
tells you how how how robust and
civilized our society is. So I think
it's a great thing. We don't need to be
a surveillance state. Uh thoughts on the
East German Stacey? Oh, it was a
terrible terrible thing. It was the
Stacey was a state
surveillance or
organization. Um and it would it would
spy on all East German citizens. It was
it it it went to such an extent that you
know inside a family you did not know
who was spying on whom. It would be
maybe that the wife is spying on the
husband and and the children. Maybe the
husband is spying on the wife or the
children or maybe a a child is spying on
the parents. That's the extent to which
they they compromise their own so
society. Terrible. Nobody would want to
have that in the country. Terrible.
Terrible. Shila says, "Now that India
has proven its power of air defense,
will what will be the updated points of
India and Chowa
index. See the the and this is coming
out soon. Now the Cha index. The way the
scores are calculated, it's calculated
based on macro
factors. What is the amount of military
in military uh expenditure of a country
per year? That's it. You can't take very
small granular details into
consideration in in calculating an index
of 191 nations. So, uh it will not make
any difference at this point in time in
the Chava index. The only thing the way
to make a difference in the travel index
is by increasing the military
expenditure of India and by you know
having more nuclear weapons warheads and
by uh by having a larger GDP and and
other things some other factors as well.
So the air defense factor it's it's
great but it doesn't make any difference
in in the composite score that's
calculated the calculated the hard power
score.
Devour of world says abijit of clan cha
first of his name. Thank you sir. Thank
you so much. Jad sakar says bj awaits
email sent. Thank you so much. I will
respond to it as soon as I can. Thank
you very much for the invitation. I
would love to come to BJ. I would love
to. Thank you so much. Rik Power says
Germany's chancellor plans to set up a
$500 billion or something to build
Europe's strongest military. Are we
heading towards part three or the
trilogy's grand
finale? We'll see about that. I hope
there is no part three. I would not want
to see a part three of the no trilogy.
World War II you're talking about. Uh
look, they are planning to do this,
planning to do that. It's all words.
Let's let's see them actually take the
action of of spending $500 billion to to
build a strong military. Then we'll
talk. And the Americans spend about a
trillion dollars a year on their
military. So with that in mind, spending
$500 billion or or pounds in one go is
nothing compared to spending a trillion
dollars a year. So I don't think it's
going to transform Europe into a
superpower. And even if they do this,
who's going to control the military?
Right? There's no strong leadership in
Europe. At the end of the the end of the
day, it's the quality of the leadership
that really matters more than anything
else. So,
um I hope there is no World War II. And
I I don't see Europe posing a
significant challenge to Russia. And if
they do pose a challenge to Russia and
Russia feels the heat, Russia is very
capable of taking very very strong
military action which would take us
towards World War II. So, I hope it
doesn't happen. I hope it doesn't
happen. Okay. Uh, Akar says, "Why do you
think we didn't we did not pound
Pakistan for 2 or 3 days more? Would the
US really have sanctioned us if we
delayed the secession of firing for 2 or
3 days?" Look, the fact that we stopped
or we paused the military action before
we achieved our objectives indicates
that some kind of very serious threat
came to the came to us from the US. What
the threat was, we don't know. It will
not be revealed in public. But the
Americans did use some form of leverage
against us which which forced us to stop
the military
operation. So I don't know what what
leverage or what threats they used but
they worked because the US is way more
powerful than India. So that's why we
stopped and we did not pound Pakistan
for two or three days more. I was hoping
that we would take P or some part of it
and we were very much in a position to
do that if if this thing continued for
another two days.
Um but yeah, the Americans came in the
way and whatever threats they used,
whatever leverage they used worked. We
don't know what they
used. Uh Zezy says, "What would happen
if the BJP got 400 seats in the
election?" I would say I would imagine
that if the BJP got 400 seats, then it
would have been a much more proactive
government and huge reforms possibly
could have happened which haven't
happened this time. So yeah, Sai says if
Pakistan gives P illegally to China,
what can we do? At this point in time,
we cannot do much. At this time, not
much. Uh so the only solution to all our
problems is to get much more stronger
than we what we are
today. Shubra Mishra says, first of all,
thank you. Uh do you think the crypto
fund supported by the US to Pakistan
will make tracing terrorism funding more
difficult or what are the long-term
effects? uh the Trump family, the Trump
business empire has significant dealings
in
cryptocurrency and uh the they are
investing in Pakistan and Pakistan is
send setting up its own cryptocurrency
fund. So this will certainly make
tracing terrorism more difficult. Right?
Cryptocurrency is untraceable. You can't
really trace who did you know who spent
how much on what. It's completely
anonymous on the ledger.
And uh yeah, so if the Trump family is
investing in cryptocurrency initiatives
in Pakistan, it it raises a lot of red
flags for
me. And this makes you know investing in
terrorism very easy and very anonymized.
So the long-term effects of that is that
they would it looks like they they
believe in the long-term future of
Pakistan and they want to see this
nation continue to exist and they want
to strengthen the nation and and
strengthening it in such a way that you
know the terrorism industry can continue
to exist and its actual funders can
remain safely and securely
anonymous. So it it tells you that
u this initiative is not good for India
and it's going to cause more frictions
between India and the United
States. Okay. Prelt says why globally
all democracy has two major parties with
two opposition parties as in counter
intelligence. Why did the government
sell H to
far? Okay. Why globally all democracies
have two major parties? I don't think
it's globally like that. Uh in the U in
the UK, you have two or three parties.
In France, I'm not sure how many parties
you have. In the US, you have two
parties. In Pakistan, you have what
Pakistan is not not a democracy. So,
let's not discuss Pakistan at all.
Um so, globally, I think only India is a
genuinely robust democracy where you
have hundreds of political parties. All
other nations are much smaller first of
all, which is why they only have two or
three parties. And in many cases these
nations mo many of them are not real
democracies because
uh uh despite elections happening uh the
people don't get to control what
happens. Look at Japan. Elections happen
every year in Japan. I mean every few
years in Japan but the fate of Japan is
controlled by the
US. It is and the military occupation
and the foreign policy and military
policy is controlled by the US and so is
the economic policy. So elections don't
matter. Elections are just an eyewash.
So in many countries democracy is just a
sham and many countries follow the the
US model or try to emulate that which
once again makes it not really a
democracy. So that's just the way the
world is you know when once you start
looking deeper into the world and the
way the world is run you will start to
see that much of what we believe to be
true is not really
true. Why did the government solve h to
far really? Okay, let me Google this
very
quickly. H A L Farese. What is
HL? H A L
Farese. Okay, I I'm not able to see any
such thing over
here. Nope. I'm not able to find any
such news. I've not heard of this news.
So I'm I'm not sure where you got this
news. Doesn't look like it's true. or
maybe maybe it
needs you know a more detailed
investigation. I'm not sure but I've not
heard of it.
So even Lord first of all thank you sir.
Uh do you think the breakdown of race
relations in the US will negatively
affect Indians? AfricanAmericans are
generally xenophobic and whites are
feeling threatened and attacked. Look
the US is going down the wrong wrong
path. Um yeah, race relations are not
there. There there seems to be a kind of
breakdown of race relations. Uh right
now the AfricanAmerican origin people
feel super empowered and
uh there's a there's a big push in the
entertainment industry to over represent
African-Americans now to perhaps
compensate for the time for the decades
when where they were under reppresented
and they are they are apparently being
over represented everywhere else also
and so on and many
people seem to feel that
African-Americans allegedly are very
xenophobic and so on. Uh white people
may be feeling threatened and attacked.
Uh one gets the sense that this is
actually true. Yeah. When you see uh the
social media uh you know activities that
come out of the US, you get the sense
that what even Lord is saying is very
much true.
Um, so there's a lot of racism on the
rise in the US and much of it is is much
of it seems to be anti-white racism and
there seems to be anti-Indian racism
also in the US. There's a rise of
anti-Indian racism. Uh, Indians for the
longest time were completely invisible
in the US. They would keep a very low
profile. They would stay out of the
limelight. They would do their job and
you know keep their heads down. But with
the coming to age of of uh you know
second generation third generation
Indians uh who are very vocal and who
are very participative in politics like
Vive Vivec Ramaswami and so on Indians
are becoming very visible and it's not
going down well with many sections of
American society who expect Indians to
remain invisible and marginalized and
that's why you are seeing a significant
uptick of anti-India anti-Indian uh
xenophobia and racism and hindu phobia
as well. So I think if things continue
the way they are continuing then this
will this could negatively affect
Indians and Indians could end up feeling
significantly threatened if this
continues. Yeah, it could happen. It
could it could go in that direction and
not just it's and I'm not saying that
Indians will feel threatened by
African-American origin people. I think
Indians may end up being feeling be
feeling threatened by everyone at large
at large including white people and
including African-Americans possibly if
things continue the way they're they're
continuing. U yeah so I hope it doesn't
happen but it doesn't seem to be looking
good right now the way things are going.
Hi says who will win deadly art of war
achar chanaki or sununzu what if they
existed in today's geopolitical
scenario well Sununzu did not rule an
empire he did not do a regime change
operation in which he defeated an
existing empire and brought a new empire
to and gave birth to a new empire did
nothing nothing nothing of the
sorty was a diplomat and he was a great
statement statesman he was responsible
for the for the downfall
of the Nanda Empire and the very rapid
rise and establishment of the Mori
Empire. He was establish he was
responsible for the mentorship of the
great emperor Chandraut Moria of
bringing him out of obscurity and
placing him as the emperor of India. So
the the achievements if you put them
side by side it's clear that Vishnu
Chanaki's achievements dwarf anything
Sunu may have done despite western
propaganda and Chinese propaganda. So I
would say Sunzu would win the art art of
war or whatever you want to call it,
right? What if they existed in today's
geopolitical scenario? Well, it would be
an interesting time if they did exist
today. And I would say if it was the
case, then it would be advantage
India. Anish, thank you sir. What are
your thoughts on the rumors of India
acquiring Bram and Kadahar air bases?
Any truth to it? And is it a good
opportunity for our nassent empire to
begin power projection? I think any
rumors of India acquiring Bagram and
Kandahar are just rumors. Uh I don't
think that's the
case. Why do I not think it's the case?
It's because the Taliban are on the US
payroll. The Taliban are the government
of Afghanistan.
uh they came to power because America
handed over the country to to the
Taliban after negotiating an agreement
in the DHA accord with the Taliban in
which there are some secret clauses and
the Taliban have been ever since been on
the payroll of the Americans. It is said
that the Taliban is paid between 30 to
$100 million in cash per week as a
stipend from the Americans. So if that
is the case then the Taliban are are
taking care of Afghanistan to a certain
extent on behalf of the Americans and
they have a an understanding a clear
understanding with the Americans which
means that there will be certain red
lines the Americans will not want to be
crossed. Now India acquiring Bagram and
Kandahar will be a huge red line for the
Americans. The Americans don't want
India to expand any influence anywhere.
They want India to remain where it
is and that's why I think this is just
rumors. I don't think India has acquired
Bagram or Kandahar. I would be very
happy if it were the case but I doubt it
very much.
Okay. Uh Amisha good to see Amisha.
North India is heating. Climate change
is real. Uh yeah climate change seems to
be real. uh in many parts of India right
now you have this premature rainy season
that has arrived and it's raining like a
month before it should be raining and in
North India at the time it looks like
there's a significant amount of heat
wave activity going on so there's no
question about the fact that climate
change is real and uh the weather is not
the way it used to be 30 40 years ago so
yes I agree climate change is real and
uh it's going to be a challenge going
forward for the future generations
Jutesh says, "Do you think India can
have the same amount of geopolitical
power and success as the US
has until 2047?" So you mean that by
2047 will be will we have the same
amount of geopolitical power and success
as the Americans? Not that much. By
2047, I'll be pleased super pleased if
India is number
two. I'll be very happy if India
surpasses China by number two. But it's
that even that is difficult. So India
want most likely if the way if things go
the way they are they they're going
right now India will be somewhere at
number three by 2047 close to China but
not it won't have surpassed China if
India really exceeds expectations we
could be close to the US but we will
most likely not have the same amount of
geopolitical power or a comparable
amount of geopolitical power and success
as what the Americans have right now by
2047. By 2075 we could be number one.
Yeah. If we get things
right. Uh Swabiar says, "What MBTI type
are you and your thoughts? I am myself
an
INTP." Well, well, well. I am
INTP. Okay. Cricket Stars Wendy, thank
you so much. Thank you so much. K dot
impersonator says new Air India JFK to
Delhi business class was better than
most others I've traveled. They're on
schedule and introduce they're on
schedule to introduce even newer cabins
this year. Excited. I'm so happy to hear
that. Excellent. So for a change they
have a good business class. Good. Looks
like they are making good progress. I'm
very pleased to hear that. Thank you for
letting us know about this JFK Delhi
business class. That's a long flight.
long flight anyhow if if it's
comfortable then it's it's a good flight
really now says is Japan more
technologically advanced than the US
will the Japanese never break the chains
how do they feel about it the youth like
South Korea seem disinterested in
politics in the military I would imagine
most Japanese are not even aware of the
fact that their country is under
permanent US military occupation it's
just seen as a normal thing most likely
is Japan more technologically advanced
than the US in some cases in certain
technologies and sectors. It is way more
advanced than the US. No question about
it. But you can you'll notice if you are
observant that Japan figures nowhere in
the AI or robotics race. Why is that?
It's because they have not been allowed
to venture into that sector. Otherwise,
they would have been ahead of China and
the US. Uh so as long as Japan is under
permanent US military occupation, they
will not be able to break the chains.
And most of see the education system in
Japan in Japan makes sure that most
Japanese don't ever realize that they
are in chains and that's so sad but
that's that's the way it
is. RPPL thank you so much sir. Dr.
Ritik Patnayak says only Odisha
resources are support are sufficient to
defeat Bangladesh. No question about it.
Orisa Kalinga is enough to defeat
Bangladesh. rest of India can just watch
and applaud. Good, good job,
Kolinga. No question. Adwit meta says,
"Thoughts on
AFD? Are they the new Nazis? I
personally don't think they are with
vital as their head." Afd? What is AFD?
Iay AFD alternative for Germany. A
faright right-wing populist and national
conservative political party in Germany.
Okay. It's the party, political party
that Elon Musk seems to support, isn't
it?
Right. And they are called what? Far
right. Which means that they want
Germany to be more independent than what
it is. You see, if you are even slightly
nationalist today, nationalistic, then
you are painted as faright. I don't
think they are new Nazis or something.
I'm not sure what their exact agenda is
but I do not think that there is any
real farright genuinely far right or
Nazi like party in Germany today. I
think um in India they would be you
would be if you are a centrist party you
would be ported as far in Germany today.
So I don't think AFD are the are the new
Nazis by by any
means. ZZ says what is consciousness
according to science? Well the answer is
according to science there is no
definition of consciousness. Science is
currently at a loss to define what
consciousness
is. Whether it's physics, a physics
perspective or neuroscience perspective,
information technology perspective or
whichever other perspective, we don't
know how to define
consciousness. So consciousness is a
phenomenon that is currently beyond the
scope of science. We know something
exists, but we don't know what it is. We
don't even know how to define it. So
science doesn't have an answer at this
point in time as to what consciousness
is. Dr. Patnak says Pakistan is a beggar
and it's a failed state. What does it
offer to the US? Pakistan offers
mercenary services to the US. It's like
a gunda for hire. Okay. And its utility
is that it can keep India off balance
when it is paid to do that. So it can
unleash terror attacks on India. It can
launch crossber strikes. it can try to
push terrorists into India and keep on
doing that over and over again as a as a
permanent nuisance and a permanent thorn
in India's flesh. That is um the value
it offers to the US. So so you see the
US doesn't want India to rise. No
existing great power wants a new power
to rise and that's why they want to keep
the nation off balance. They want to
keep the nation suppressed and you can
use gundas like Pakistan to keep nations
like India off balance. So that is the
value it offers to the US. Very
valuable. K dot um impersonator says
India China allied future possibilities
or options. It's very difficult for me
to see an India China alliance going
forward. Um the Chinese have a whole
different worldview. They have a whole
different u envisioned future for the
world. It's a future in which they don't
they don't they don't want to see an a
rising India a powerful India and uh
that's why the the Chinese and Pakistan
that's what the Chinese and the
Americans see eye to eye when it comes
to Pakistan they both want Pakistan to
continue existing and and they both want
Pakistan to be reasonably strong and and
resilient against India. uh so I it's
very hard for me to see a future
scenario in which India and China become
kind of allies or even cooperate in a
wide range of issues. Uh the Chinese
they don't see India's equals. They're
right not to see India as equals because
India because China is about three and a
half times more powerful than India
right now. A much larger economy, more
advanced technologically, better living
standards, better quality of life,
better education system, uh stronger
larger military and so on so forth. Why
would they see India as an equal? So
when you have a nation that you don't
see as an equal, then you will want to
keep that nation off balance and you
don't want the nation uh to rise until
they become your equal and that's why
they have kept the Tibet border issue
open for for all these decades the India
Tibet border it is still undemarcated
because the Chinese want to use that as
a as a pressure tactic and so on. So
it's very hard for me to see a future
India China alliance. It would it would
be great if if that happens. You know,
China is a wonderful civilization. Used
to be and we in India have had excellent
relations with China for 2,000 years.
It's only in the last 60, 70, 80 years
that things have gone bad because of the
Chinese Communist Party's annexation of
Tibet, which always was independent. So
yeah, that's the deal.
Spade says came across Hitler's speech
which criticized Jews in power for not
openly calling and not openly calling
for violence. Said they created state
within state to trick passes into
feeling like kingmakers when it's in
illusion. Heck knew back
then. Uh okay. So I'm not sure if
there's a question over here. Uh a lot
of old speeches of Adolf Fet are now
coming to light. In the past nobody had
translations of these speeches but today
because of AI you can have instantaneous
translations into your preferred
language whe whether it's English or
anything else. So today you can get to
actually understand what Hitler was
saying and u so people are trying to are
beginning to revisit Hitler and maybe
perhaps see him and his actions and his
speeches in a new light maybe and it's a
process of you know historical
rediscovery or whatever it is. So I'm
not sure what he has I have not I have
not really bothered to look into his
speeches and examine and study what he
was saying. So I'm not sure what what he
may or may not have said. Uh but yeah
the it's it's interesting that this is
happening at this at this point in
time. Um Kumar says my mind won't let me
doesn't let me read 1,00 page books. Any
tips? My tip is that you know what it's
not important it's not necessary to read
10,00 to read 1,00 page books. It's not
for everybody. If your mind doesn't want
to do it, don't force it. You know, play
to your strengths. It's not important.
It's not necessary for everybody to read
to read gigantic books. Not not
important. Not necessary. So, don't
force yourself. You can succeed very
well without having to do that. Dr. Rit
Patnak says, "What if Russia intervened
and supported India when US came in
between and told for ceasefire?"
tell something about India's relations
with Russia and
Israel. Russia was not in a position to
intervene and support India. See, the
Americans came in the way and they
issued some kind of threat that made
India stop
immediately. I'm not sure what the
threat was, but they issued some kind of
threat. Now, what can Russia do to
prevent the threat from
happening? The threat would most likely
have been some kind of economic threat.
Maybe something else also. Can Russia
prevent the Americans from unleashing
economic warfare on India for example.
Russia can't. So what can Russia do is
the question. Russia is not that
powerful today. Please understand
that. So what if Russia intervene? The
question is can Russia even intervene?
And the answer is no. Russia cannot. So
that's the reality of life. Our
relationship our relations with Russia
are very very old going back decades and
very good relations. They have overall
been a reliable partner and a good
partner for India and Israel. We have a
more recent relationship but this is a
good relationship. It's based on mutual
interests and strategic convergence. So
that's also a good relationship and we
should invest in both these
relationships. Okay, we are reaching the
3hour mark. So in case you're trying to
put more questions, I would say please
stop giving stop buying more super chats
because otherwise I will not be able to
answer all your questions. So next
question is by Kajoro Bathon. Thoughts
on Dr. John Seal's Chinese room
experiment that proves that a computer
can never have consciousness. Do you
agree? I'm not aware of this experiment
but very interesting that when I have
super chats, I get all these interesting
questions that I'm not aware of. So let
me quickly Google this. Dr. John Seal
John
Seal Chinese room. Interesting. What is
this? Let's find out. Chinese room
argument.
Um Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy.
The argument and thought experiment now
generally known as the Chinese room. A
1980 article. What what does it mean?
What does it say?
Seal imagines himself alone in a room
following a computer program to for
responding to Chinese characters slipped
under the door. He understands nothing
of Chinese and yet by following the
program for manipulating symbols and
numerals just like a computer does, he
sends appropriate strings of Chinese
characters back out under the door and
this leads to those those outside to
mistakenly suppose that there is a
Chinese speaker in the room. So he's
following a computer program. The narrow
conclusion seal rose from the experiment
is that programming a digital computer
might make it appear to understand
language but could not produce real
understanding. Hence, the Turing test is
inadequate. Seir argues that the thought
experiment underscores the fact that
computers merely use syntactic rules to
manipulate symbol strings but have no
understanding of meaning or
semantics. Okay, very interesting
thought experiment.
Does it prove that a computer can never
have consciousness? No. It only proves
that if you able to produce Chinese
characters like a person who understands
Chinese, it doesn't necessarily mean
that it's come from a conscious
source. It doesn't prove that there can
be no consciousness ever in a
computer. No, I don't agree with that.
So this experiment is very interesting.
It proves that if you are on the other
side of the door and Dr. John Seal is is
slipping you Chinese characters as if he
knows Chinese. It proves that it it may
not be the case, but it doesn't disprove
the possibility of a computer ever
having consciousness. So yeah, these are
two different
things. Okay. Spade says why was Shinszo
Abbe killed? He was moving towards China
Russia camp. Recently his wife made
appearance with Putin. I don't think
Shinszu Abbe was moving towards towards
the China Russia camp. Shinszu AB was a
great patriot. He wanted more
independence from Japan. He wanted Japan
to break free of the American occupation
of the American shackles. He wanted u he
wanted the Japanese constitution to be
amended to give Japan the right to fight
war if required. See the Japanese
constitution was written in 1945 by the
Americans. And since the day it was
written in 1945 until today, not a
single word has been changed. That's how
that's one of the ways that Japan is
enslaved. So he wanted to change the
constitution to amend the constitution
to make it uh legal for Japan to have a
standing armed force and to engage in
war as an instrument of national uh
interest. And maybe that's why he was
killed. Maybe that's why he was killed.
I mean what what happened to his
assassin? He he the whole thing has been
brushed under the carpet, right? Yeah.
That's how it goes. Okay. Nomad Hustle
says, "My 13-year-old nephew needs to
start reading newspapers to improve
awareness and
vocabulary. Hindu Indo-Uropeans are too
biased." Hindu Indian. Okay. Okay.
Sorry. The Hindu is a newspaper. The
Indian Express is a newspaper too biased
according to Mr. Nomad and Times of
India and and Hindustan Times are too
crass. Any paper with balance, quality
and national interest in mind. I don't
read newspapers. I I've stopped reading
newspapers a long time ago. I have
absolutely no idea if there's any paper
today in India with balanced quality and
national interest in mind. I gave up on
newspapers a long time ago. All just
useless. So I don't know. I don't read
newspapers anymore. I get all my sources
of all my information from online
sources from a vast multitude of online
sources. There's no one online source
that stands out. So I just don't know if
I can give you any answer. My I would
say consume information from a wide
360deree perspective online. Newspapers
I don't know. I think newspapers have
become a thing of the past. Sorry I
can't give you any direction because I
am no longer connected to that
world. Sudaran says what if most stars
turn into black holes that merge into
one another? Is that not contra
contraction blue shift next stage of
liarak con concept as said in withers
but why would most stars turn into black
holes most stars are physically
incapable of turning into black
holes right look there is something
called the chandraher limit 1.44 44 uh
solar mass which is the limit beyond
which a star becomes a neutron star and
then there's a higher mass limit beyond
which a star will eventually collapse
into a black hole. Most stars don't
satisfy this condition. So how will most
stars turn into black holes? And even if
most stars turn into black holes why
will they merge into each other when the
universe is expanding rapidly and the
expansion is accelerating? Even if they
turn into black holes they will never
merge into each other. So yeah, so
interesting thought experiment that
you're proposing sir, but it it is not
consistent with what we know about the
universe. So it's not going to happen.
Sorry. Sorry about that. I don't know
what liar concept is in
Vas. Dr. Rituk Patnak says, "Is Sai
Sudashan more talented than Gilanj?" I'm
not watching the IPL, so I don't know.
Sai Sudashan is a left arm spinner or a
batsman? Not sure. I have not watched
the IPL. Not sure. Sorry. Sorry.
Phoneography says if Pakistan breaks up
and the Taliban takes Kibar Pakuna and
we take Pakistan Jammu and Kashmir, we
will be neighbors. Will peace be
possible? Should we only take Gil with
Baltistan? Not P radicals. We should
take back whatever territory was other
was ours. Okay. Is ours? We should take
it all back. And what if we and the
Taliban are neighbors? We have no issues
with each other. As long as there is no
territorial dispute and as long as we
don't interfere in each other's internal
affairs, there's no issue. I would like
us to be again neighbors with Gandhar
and with
Persia. Of course, peace is possible.
Peace is possible through through
strength and mutual respect. So, we
should take back everything that is ours
for sure. Even Lord says, "Do you see
the US as a democracy/ republic that's
approaching a monarchy or a
dictatorship?" Thank you. Okay. I see
the US as a as an empire. The US is an
empire and it is an autocracy
masquerading as a democracy because the
US is a two-party system, right? Which
is just one step above the Chinese
Communist Party's one party rule or
North Korea's one party rule. And when
it comes to the US political parties,
there are only two that really matter.
The others are just there for salad
dressing. uh and the two American
political parties, the Republicans and
the Democrats, they have essentially the
same foreign policy and very much the
same international policy and and
international economic policy. It's only
in in domestic politics that they are
different from each other. So
essentially you have a uniarty system
masquerading as a democracy. So the US
is a global empire and it's an
autocracy. That's how I see it.
Rudra says, "RCB aka Virat Kohli team
have reached final." Well, I I hear that
RCB has never won the IPL. So, if you
are an RCB supporter, maybe this time
they'll win. All right. Good. Good to
know that. And good for Mr. Kohli. And
Rajat Rastoi has donated 6.99. Thank you
so much, sir. I really appreciate that.
And with that, we have come to the end
of the super chats.
Fantastic. That is it. Rdra says, "Is
this live?" Well, it wouldn't be live if
I I mean it's live because I've taken
your question in real time. Okay. Abira
says, "Is Saisan is an opening batsman?"
All right. Okay. So, with that, we have
come to the end of today's live stream.
Thank you very much everybody for all
your questions. Okay. There's one more
question. Apparently, this should be the
last one for today. Suranjan Kumar
Biswar says, "Is being a proud Hindu a
bad thing in the US?" It seems like they
don't like us and they preach democracy
and human rights. Look, the US is a
Christian
nation in God we trust. Which God? The
Abrahamic God. The Christian God. It may
be technically not a religious nation.
Technically, technically it may not be a
religion oriented nation or a nation
with the state religion, but overall
it's a Christian nation, right? And uh
and the West doesn't understand
polytheism. They used to be
polytheists way back. Their culture,
their religion was the was an extension
of our religion, the old Indo-Uropean
religion. But they lost it a long time
ago. It was smashed out of existence by
the Abrahamics and Christianity became a
thing. And today the Americans don't
understand. The Americans, the West, the
Europeans, nobody understands
polytheism. We are the only polytheistic
culture that survives. And we are the
oldest continuously existing
civilization that still exists today.
And u yeah so being a polytheist is
actually seen as a bad thing in a
monotheistic or a dominated culture. So
being a proud Hindu is even bad even
worse. How dare you be proud of being a
polytheist. So yeah the dislike will be
there and it will be usually kept in the
wraps but it will rear its ugly head
from from time to time. And it's just
the way it is. It's just the way their
culture is constructed and the way they
see things. That's the worldview that
they have that polytheism is evil. It's
bad. Uh but yeah, this is the this is
the culture that this is the country
that preaches democracy and human rights
while treating people are not the same.
But that's how the world goes. The world
is a web of
contradictions. And if if a nation is
being hypocritical, it means that they
are really powerful. So it's a privilege
to be hypocrite in in the geopolitical
world order.
All right everybody, thank you so much
for all of your
questions. I'm going to end this live
stream here. Monday we begin a new
series Geost Strategy with Abijit Cha
and it's going to be followed by an Ask
Abijit session once that live stream
ends. So I hope to see all of you on
Monday 8:00 p.m. and I'm going to put
out next big schedule tomorrow. So,
thank you so much for all your questions
and I will see you in the next live
stream which will happen very soon.
Until then, take care, keep raising your
standards and I'll see you very soon.
Thank you.